<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="case-report" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">World J Nucl Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">World J Nucl Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1617</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">wjnucmed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>World Journal of Nuclear Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1450-1147</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1607-3312</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Thieme Medical Publishers</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12774523</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12774523.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12774523</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12774523</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41502996</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0045-1809310</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">WJNM-25-3-0005</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Diagnostic Challenges in a Case of Suspected Breast Cancer with Low FDG Uptake and an Incidental Thyroid Lesion: A Case Report and Literature Review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0009-0008-9224-8965</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Amalo</surname><given-names initials="RB">Raydel Briankwee</given-names></name><xref rid="AF2530005-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="CO2530005-1" ref-type="author-notes"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuti</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yustia</given-names></name><xref rid="AF2530005-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dewi</surname><given-names initials="AR">Ayu Rosemeilia</given-names></name><xref rid="AF2530005-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AF2530005-1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Nuclear Medicine and Theranostic Molecular, School of Medicine, Universitas Padjajaran, Hasan Sadikin General Hospital, Bandung, Indonesia</institution></aff><aff id="AF2530005-2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Nuclear Medicine and Theranostic Molecular, Dharmais Cancer General Hospital, Jakarta, Indonesia</institution></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CO2530005-1"><bold>Address for correspondence </bold>Raydel Briankwee Amalo, MD <institution>Department of Nuclear Medicine and Theranostic Molecular, School of Medicine, Universitas Padjajaran</institution><addr-line>Hasan Sadikin General Hospital, Bandung</addr-line><country>Indonesia</country><email>Ray_amalo@hotmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>24</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">504315</issue-id><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>376</lpage><history/><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>07</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-01-08 09:25:13.073"><day>08</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>
The Author(s). This is an open access article published by Thieme under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, permitting unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction so long as the original work is properly cited. (
<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</uri>
)
</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s).</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="10-1055-s-0045-1809310.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>The coexistence of multiple malignancies presents diagnostic and therapeutic challenges. Breast and thyroid cancers are among the most frequently diagnosed malignancies in women, and studies suggest a potential bidirectional association. While fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG)-positron emission tomography (PET)/computed tomography (CT) is a valuable imaging modality for evaluating breast cancer, its sensitivity in detecting low-metabolic subtypes remains limited. Additionally, incidental FDG-avid thyroid lesions require further evaluation due to their potential malignancy risk.</p></sec><sec><title>Case Report</title><p>We present a 61-year-old female with a suspected left breast malignancy, suggestive of luminal A subtype, showing low FDG uptake (maximum standardized uptake value [SUVmax] 2.0) on PET/CT, despite mammographic and ultrasound findings suggestive of malignancy (Breast Imaging-Reporting and Data System 4A and V). Additionally, an incidental left thyroid lesion (4.0&#8201;&#215;&#8201;3.8&#8201;cm, SUVmax 3.4) with calcifications was detected, raising suspicion for malignancy. The discordant imaging findings in this case highlight the limitations of FDG-PET/CT and emphasize the necessity of multimodal imaging and histopathological confirmation.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>This case underscores the importance of integrating multiple imaging modalities for accurate diagnosis. While PET/CT is useful for systemic staging, its limitations in detecting certain breast cancer subtypes necessitate complementary imaging techniques and histopathological confirmation. The incidental thyroid lesion also required further assessment, reinforcing the need for a comprehensive diagnostic approach.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords</title><kwd>bidirectional breast and thyroid cancer</kwd><kwd>breast cancer</kwd><kwd>dual malignancy</kwd><kwd>incidentaloma thyroid</kwd><kwd>low FDG Uptake</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>
Breast and thyroid cancers are commonly diagnosed malignancies in women, with epidemiological evidence suggesting a bidirectional association.
<xref rid="JR2530005-1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
Fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG)-positron emission tomography (PET)/computed tomography (CT) is widely used in breast cancer staging, particularly for aggressive subtypes, but has limitations in detecting low-metabolic tumors. Incidental FDG-avid thyroid lesions require careful assessment due to their malignancy potential.
<xref rid="JR2530005-2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
This case underscores the need for a multidisciplinary approach in diagnosing coexisting malignancies.
</p></sec><sec><title>Case Presentation</title><p>A 61-year-old female presented with a palpable left breast lump persisting for 6 months. She had a history of hypertension managed with amlodipine. Physical examination revealed no significant lymphadenopathy in the bilateral axillae and cervical regions.</p><sec><title>Imaging Findings</title><p>Breast ultrasound (December 2024): Left breast lesion (1.15&#8201;&#215;&#8201;1.25&#8201;&#215;&#8201;1.43&#8201;cm), irregular margins, internal vascularization, and Breast Imaging-Reporting and Data System (BIRADS) V classification.</p><p>Mammography (February 2025): Indeterminate left breast nodule (0.6&#8201;&#215;&#8201;0.6&#8201;cm) with amorphous microcalcifications, BIRADS 4A classification.</p><p>
PET/CT (February 2025): Left breast lesion (1.7&#8201;&#215;&#8201;1.5&#8201;cm) with low FDG uptake (maximum standardized uptake value [SUVmax] 2.0), metabolically inactive axillary lymphadenopathy, and an incidental left thyroid lesion (4.0&#8201;&#215;&#8201;3.8&#8201;cm, SUVmax 3.4) (
<xref rid="FI2530005-1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
).
</p><p>Subsequent thyroid ultrasonography (US) revealed a nodule classified as Thyroid Imaging Reporting and Data System 5, indicating a high suspicion of malignancy.</p><fig id="FI2530005-1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>
(
<bold>A</bold>
) Maximum intensity projection (MIP) positron emission tomography (PET)/computed tomography (CT) image showing increased fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG) uptake in the left breast and left thyroid lobe. (
<bold>B</bold>
) Axial fused PET/CT image demonstrating FDG-avid lesion in the left breast. (
<bold>C</bold>
) Corresponding axial CT image revealing a left breast lesion measuring 1.7&#8201;&#215;&#8201;1.5&#8201;cm. (
<bold>D</bold>
) Axial fused PET/CT image demonstrating FDG uptake in the left thyroid lobe. (
<bold>E</bold>
) Corresponding axial CT image showing a left thyroid nodule measuring 4.0&#8201;&#215;&#8201;3.8&#8201;cm.
</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10-1055-s-0045-1809310-i2530005-1.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Mammographic (BIRADS 4A) and ultrasonographic (BIRADS V) findings suggested malignancy, but PET/CT demonstrated low FDG uptake (SUVmax 2.0), inconsistent with aggressive breast carcinoma. Despite a low SUVmax, biopsy remains crucial, as mammographic features such as microcalcifications and irregular edges strongly correlate with malignancy. PET/CT has limitations in detecting microcalcifications and low-FDG tumors, making mammography more reliable for early malignancy detection. Consequently, histopathologic biopsy remains the gold standard.</p><p>
According to the National Comprehensive Cancer Network 2024 guidelines, BIRADS 4A lesions require biopsy regardless of SUVmax due to a strong malignancy correlation.
<xref rid="JR2530005-3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
The European Association of Nuclear Medicine-Society of Nuclear Medicine and Molecular Imaging 2024 guidelines highlight that FDG-PET/CT is highly effective for triple-negative breast cancer (TNBC) and HER2+ cancers but less so for estrogen receptor-positive (ER&#8201;+&#8201;) tumors (luminal A/B) due to lower glucose metabolism.
<xref rid="JR2530005-2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
Invasive lobular carcinoma also exhibits lower FDG uptake than no special type subtypes, reducing PET sensitivity.
<xref rid="JR2530005-3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
A meta-analysis found that high SUVmax is associated with poorer outcomes (hazard ratio 2.65; 95% confidence interval [CI] 1.31&#8211;5.37;
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
&#8201;=&#8201;0.007), though thresholds vary (5.5&#8211;11.1 for primary tumors, 2.2&#8211;2.8 for axillary nodes).
<xref rid="JR2530005-4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
In this case, an SUVmax of 2.0 suggests lower aggressiveness.
</p><p>
FDG-PET/CT plays a key role in staging stage IIB to III breast cancer, with superior accuracy in axillary node and distant metastasis detection. It is crucial for assessing neoadjuvant therapy response, particularly in TNBC and HER2+ cases, and is valuable for detecting recurrence before curative interventions.
<xref rid="JR2530005-3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
<xref rid="JR2530005-5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
Studies report that FDG-avid breast lesions with calcifications have a malignancy rate of 67.8%, increasing to 76.2% if categorized as BIRADS &#8805; 4 on CT.
<xref rid="JR2530005-6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
Moreover, FDG uptake without calcification but with irregular margins is also strongly associated with malignancy. Dong et al found that 88.2% of malignant lesions with FDG uptake had irregular margins on CT.
<xref rid="JR2530005-7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
</p><p>
SUVmax does not always indicate benignity. Luminal A (3.32&#8201;&#177;&#8201;2.60) and luminal B (HER2-negative) (4.74&#8201;&#177;&#8201;2.69) tumors exhibit lower SUVmax than TNBC (9.86&#8201;&#177;&#8201;3.24) due to metabolic differences. Luminal tumors rely on oxidative phosphorylation, whereas TNBC and HER2+ tumors depend on anaerobic glycolysis. A cutoff SUVmax of &#8804; 5.46 predicts luminal tumors but lacks specificity, whereas SUVmax of &#8805; 6.33 is more reliable for TNBC classification. Despite the low SUVmax of 2.0 in this case, mammography findings (BIRADS 4A) still indicate possible malignancy.
<xref rid="JR2530005-8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
</p><p>
In thyroid cancer, incidental FDG uptake suggests a higher malignancy risk.
<xref rid="BR2530005-9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
US and physical examination are crucial for evaluation, with irregular margins, microcalcifications, and infiltrative borders being strong malignancy indicators. Large (&gt; 4&#8201;cm) or solitary nodules carry a malignancy risk of up to 19.3%.
<xref rid="JR2530005-10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
Hard, fixed nodules or cervical lymphadenopathy further increase suspicion, while vocal cord immobility suggests recurrent laryngeal nerve involvement (positive predictive value 100%).
<xref rid="JR2530005-11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
In this case, the left lobe measured 4.0&#8201;&#215;&#8201;3.8&#8201;cm with solid cystic nodules and calcifications, without cervical lymphadenopathy or vocal cord immobility.
</p><p>
Thyroid incidentalomas are found in 1 to 4% of PET/CT scans. Bae et al report a malignancy risk of 30.9% for focal FDG uptake and 6.4% for diffuse uptake. The mean SUVmax for benign nodules is 3.35&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.69, whereas malignant nodules exhibit higher SUVmax (6.64&#8201;&#177;&#8201;4.12). With an SUVmax of 3.4, further evaluation via US and fine-needle aspiration was recommended.
<xref rid="JR2530005-12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
Chun et al found thyroid incidentalomas with FDG uptake have a malignancy risk of 27.8 to 74%, with malignant nodules showing a median SUV of 4.7 (interquartile range [IQR] 3.4&#8211;6.0) and benign nodules of 2.8 (IQR 2.6&#8211;4.0).
<xref rid="JR2530005-13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
Stangierski et al report malignancy risk at 16.7% for SUVmax&#8201;&lt;&#8201;3.0, 43.8% for SUVmax 3 to 6, and 54.6% for SUVmax&#8201;&gt;&#8201;6.
<xref rid="JR2530005-14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
Bolf et al found that women with thyroid cancer have a higher risk of developing breast cancer.
<xref rid="JR2530005-15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
Supporting this, a Mendelian randomization study by Tan et al identified a causal relationship between ER+ breast cancer and an increased risk of thyroid cancer (odds ratio [OR]&#8201;=&#8201;1.135, 95% CI: 1.006&#8211;1.279,
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
&#8201;=&#8201;0.038), while no significant association was found with TNBC.
<xref rid="JR2530005-16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
</p><p>
Several studies suggest a bidirectional association between breast and thyroid cancers. Meta-analyses show an increased risk of thyroid cancer following breast cancer (OR 1.55) and vice versa (OR 1.32).
<xref rid="JR2530005-1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
Shared genetic mutations (PTEN, BRCA1/2) and hormonal influences (estrogen receptor expression) contribute to this link.
<xref rid="JR2530005-15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
<xref rid="JR2530005-17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
Cancer treatments, including radiation therapy and radioactive iodine-131, may further impact risk.
</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>This case underscores the diagnostic complexities of malignancies with discordant imaging findings. While mammographic and ultrasonographic features strongly suggested breast malignancy, the low FDG uptake on PET/CT emphasized the limitations of metabolic imaging in certain breast cancer subtypes. Similarly, the incidental thyroid lesion with an SUVmax of 3.4 necessitated further evaluation to determine its malignant potential. A comprehensive approach, integrating clinical assessment, imaging modalities, and histopathological confirmation, remains crucial in guiding appropriate management strategies for patients with suspected multiple primary malignancies.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="d35e83"><p><bold>Conflict of Interest</bold> None declared.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="JR2530005-1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>S M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>M G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>The breast-thyroid cancer link: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source><year>2016</year><volume>25</volume><issue>02</issue><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26908594</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-15-0833</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4770576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR2530005-2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hindi&#233;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hindi&#233;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The EANM-SNMMI guideline on the role of [18F]FDG-PET/CT in breast cancer: important milestones and perspectives for the future</article-title><source>Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging</source><year>2024</year><volume>51</volume><issue>09</issue><fpage>2695</fpage><lpage>2700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38735885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00259-024-06758-y</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR2530005-3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carkaci</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adrada</surname><given-names>B E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rohren</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Semiquantitative analysis of maximum standardized uptake values of regional lymph nodes in inflammatory breast cancer: is there a reliable threshold for differentiating benign from malignant?</article-title><source>Acad Radiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>19</volume><issue>05</issue><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>541</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22300741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.acra.2012.01.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4128395</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR2530005-4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>Y J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D I</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Prognostic value of SUVmax in breast cancer and comparative analyses of molecular subtypes: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Medicine (Baltimore)</source><year>2021</year><volume>100</volume><issue>31</issue><fpage>e26745</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34397816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MD.0000000000026745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8341324</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR2530005-5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gradishar</surname><given-names>W J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>M S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Breast cancer, version 3.2024</article-title><source>J Natl Compr Canc Netw</source><year>2024</year><volume>22</volume><issue>05</issue><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39019058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.6004/jnccn.2024.0035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR2530005-6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>R M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Mahony</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Keeffe</surname><given-names>S A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of the breast radiologist in evaluation of breast incidentalomas detected on 18-fludeoxyglucose positron emission tomography/CT</article-title><source>Br J Radiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>86</volume><issue>1026</issue><fpage>2.0130034E7</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1259/bjr.20130034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3664982</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23568361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR2530005-7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spectrum of the breast lesions with increased 18F-FDG uptake on PET/CT</article-title><source>Clin Nucl Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>41</volume><issue>07</issue><fpage>543</fpage><lpage>557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26975010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/RLU.0000000000001203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4902325</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR2530005-8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukushima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Prognostic value of SUVmax of 18F-FDG PET/CT in early-stage breast cancer with no lymph node metastasis</article-title><source>Open J Med Imaging.</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><issue>03</issue><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>123</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="BR2530005-9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aktolun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>S J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nuclear Oncology</article-title><edition>1st ed.</edition><publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name><year>2014</year></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR2530005-10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCoy</surname><given-names>K L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jabbour</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogilvie</surname><given-names>J B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohori</surname><given-names>N P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carty</surname><given-names>S E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yim</surname><given-names>J H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The incidence of cancer and rate of false-negative cytology in thyroid nodules greater than or equal to 4&#8201;cm in size</article-title><source>Surgery</source><year>2007</year><volume>142</volume><issue>06</issue><fpage>837</fpage><lpage>844</lpage>, discussion 844.e1&#8211;844.e3<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18063065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.surg.2007.08.012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR2530005-11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raza</surname><given-names>S N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>M D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palme</surname><given-names>C E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>F T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>J L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for well-differentiated thyroid carcinoma in patients with thyroid nodular disease</article-title><source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source><year>2008</year><volume>139</volume><issue>01</issue><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18585556</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.otohns.2007.10.021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR2530005-12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>J S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chae</surname><given-names>B J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>W C</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Incidental thyroid lesions detected by FDG-PET/CT: prevalence and risk of thyroid cancer</article-title><source>World J Surg Oncol</source><year>2009</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>63</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19664272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1477-7819-7-63</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2732624</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR2530005-13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>A R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>H M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S H</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Risk of malignancy in thyroid incidentalomas identified by fluorodeoxyglucose-positron emission tomography</article-title><source>Endocrinol Metab (Seoul)</source><year>2015</year><volume>30</volume><issue>01</issue><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25325277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3803/EnM.2015.30.1.71</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4384680</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR2530005-14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stangierski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woli&#324;ski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Czepczy&#324;ski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>The usefulness of standardized uptake value in differentiation between benign and malignant thyroid lesions detected incidentally in 18F-FDG PET/CT examination</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e109612</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25296297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0109612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4190406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR2530005-15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolf</surname><given-names>E L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sprague</surname><given-names>B L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>F E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A linkage between thyroid and breast cancer: a common etiology?</article-title><source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source><year>2019</year><volume>28</volume><issue>04</issue><fpage>643</fpage><lpage>649</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30541751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-18-0877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR2530005-16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between breast cancer and thyroid cancer risk: a two-sample Mendelian randomization study</article-title><source>Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1.138149E6</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fendo.2023.1138149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10242035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37288296</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="JR2530005-17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakos</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#193;rvai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><etal/><article-title>Co-occurrence of thyroid and breast cancer is associated with an increased oncogenic SNP burden</article-title><source>BMC Cancer</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><issue>01</issue><fpage>706</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34130653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12885-021-08377-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8207626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>