<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Pharmacol Toxicol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Pharmacol Toxicol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1953</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcphartox</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Pharmacology &amp; Toxicology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2050-6511</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12784584</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12784584.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12784584</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12784584</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41495854</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40360-025-01082-z</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1082</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Integrated in silico and in vitro evaluation of Genistein and Apigenin as dual inhibitors of PARP1 and ESR1 in breast cancer</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0009-0003-0633-6621</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Arora</surname><given-names initials="M">Monica</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0009-0002-2026-7522</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Yaseen</surname><given-names initials="YS">Yahya S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4915-417X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmood</surname><given-names initials="AAR">Ammar A. Razzak</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sangi</surname><given-names initials="SMA">Sibghatullah Muhammad Ali</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2058-255X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagaraja</surname><given-names initials="S">Sreeharsha</given-names></name><address><email>sharsha@kfu.edu.sa</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0009-0007-0454-2471</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurmi</surname><given-names initials="SPC">Santosh Prasad Chaudhary</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1801-5668</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Thapa</surname><given-names initials="S">Shankar</given-names></name><address><email>tshankar551@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/005azck40</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0558 9467</institution-id><institution>Faculty of Health Sciences, </institution><institution>Villa College, </institution></institution-wrap>QI Campus, Rahdhebai Hingun, Male&#8217;, 20373 Republic of Maldives </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01zfzax10</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.442858.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1796 0518</institution-id><institution>Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry, College of Pharmacy, </institution><institution>University of Tikrit, </institution></institution-wrap>Tikrit, Iraq </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/007f1da21</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411498.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2108 8169</institution-id><institution>Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry, College of Pharmacy, </institution><institution>University of Baghdad, </institution></institution-wrap>Baghdad, Iraq </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03myd1n81</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.449023.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1771 7446</institution-id><institution>Basic Medical Sciences Department, </institution><institution>Dar Al Uloom University, College of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>Riyadh, 13314 Saudi Arabia </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00dn43547</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412140.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1755 9687</institution-id><institution>Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences, College of Clinical Pharmacy, </institution><institution>King Faisal University, </institution></institution-wrap>Al-Ahsa, 31982 Saudi Arabia </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/050z7zv36</institution-id><institution>Department of Pharmacy, </institution><institution>Universal College of Medical Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Bhairahawa, 32900 Nepal </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>27</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">503730</issue-id><elocation-id>7</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>06</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>10</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-01-10 00:25:12.930"><day>10</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2026</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2026</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="40360_2025_Article_1082.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1" abstract-type="structured"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Breast cancer remains a leading cause of cancer-related mortality among women worldwide, highlighting the need for safer multitarget therapies. Genistein (GNT) and Apigenin are plant-derived flavonoids with reported anticancer properties, but their dual mechanisms against key breast cancer targets have not been comprehensively explored.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">An integrative in silico approach was employed, including network pharmacology, onco-omics profiling, protein&#8211;protein interaction analysis, molecular docking, and 100 ns molecular dynamics (MD) simulations, to identify and validate key targets of GNT and Apigenin. Gene expression, immune infiltration, and survival analyses were performed using GEPIA2 and TIMER2.0. ADMET and toxicity predictions assessed drug-likeness and safety. Cytotoxic activity was evaluated in HCC1937 cells, a triple-negative breast cancer cell line selected to assess estrogen receptor&#8211;independent anticancer effects, using the MTT assay.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Network analysis prioritized PARP1 and ESR1 as central targets. Docking showed strong affinities of Apigenin for PARP1 (&#8211;9.6&#160;kcal/mol) and GNT for ESR1 (&#8211;8.3&#160;kcal/mol). MD simulations and MM-GBSA confirmed stable binding with favorable free energy (&#916;G_bind = &#8722;&#8201;74.9&#160;kcal/mol). KEGG enrichment highlighted pathways including estrogen signaling, endocrine resistance, and PI3K&#8211;Akt signaling. Both compounds exhibited favorable ADMET profiles and low predicted toxicity. In vitro, GNT and Apigenin produced dose-dependent cytotoxicity against HCC1937 cells with IC<sub>50</sub> values of 67.01&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.67 &#181;M and 70.24&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.45 &#181;M, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">These findings demonstrate that GNT and Apigenin modulate key oncogenic pathways through PARP1 and ESR1 interaction and exert cytotoxic effects in TNBC cells. This suggests their potential as low-toxicity adjuvant agents in breast cancer therapy, particularly where endocrine resistance or BRCA1-associated tumor progression is involved.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s40360-025-01082-z.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Apigenin</kwd><kwd>Breast cancer</kwd><kwd>ESR1</kwd><kwd>GNT</kwd><kwd>Network pharmacology</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2026</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">Cancer is the leading cause of death worldwide, with 2.3 million women diagnosed with breast cancer in 2022, resulting in 670,000 fatalities globally. While breast cancer primarily affects women&#8212;about 99% of cases&#8212;it also impacts around 0.5 to 1% of men. Patients with metastatic or advanced breast cancer often face significant treatment challenges, such as side effects, drug resistance, and a lack of targeted therapies. This highlights the urgent need for the development of safer and more effective treatment options [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Natural products have emerged as promising anticancer agents owing to their favorable safety profiles, cost-effectiveness, and reduced adverse effects compared to conventional chemotherapeutics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. &#8220;Several clinically important agents, including irinotecan, vincristine, etoposide, and paclitaxel (plant-derived), actinomycin D and mitomycin C (microbial origin), and bleomycin (marine-derived), trace their origins to natural products. Many of these remain integral to current cancer treatment regimens and are expected to retain therapeutic relevance in the future&#8221; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">Breast cancer is clinically classified into major molecular subtypes, including hormone receptor&#8211;positive (ER/PR+), HER2-enriched, and triple negative breast cancer (TNBC). TNBC lacks the expression of ER, PR, and HER2 amplification, resulting in more aggressive tumor behavior, early metastasis, and limited targeted treatment options [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Unlike ER-positive breast cancers, TNBC does not benefit from endocrine therapies, making chemotherapy the primary treatment modality. Therefore, identifying low-toxicity compounds capable of modulating oncogenic pathways in TNBC is of significant therapeutic interest [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. In this context, evaluating Genistein (GNT) and Apigenin in a TNBC model, such as the HCC1937 cell line, allows investigation of their anticancer potential in an estrogen receptor&#8211;independent background.</p><p id="Par7">GNT, a soy-derived isoflavone, has been studied for its potential in breast cancer therapy due to its estrogenic effects and antioxidant properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. It acts by modulating oestrogen receptor &#946;, inhibiting angiogenesis, causing cell cycle arrest, and inducing apoptosis. Epigenetic changes and age-related differences also play a role in its anticancer activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. It targets key receptors such as estrogen receptor (ER), as well as various signalling pathways, showing effectiveness across different breast cancer cell lines. GNT&#8217;s mechanisms involve upregulating tumor suppressor genes, downregulating oncogenes, and acting synergistically with standard treatments. Both in vitro and in vivo studies support its potential as a chemopreventive and therapeutic agent in breast cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Ou et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. investigated the anti-cancer effects of Apigenin, a plant-derived flavonoid, on breast cancer stem cells (BCSCs) using a combination of network pharmacology and experimental validation. The study identified key signalling pathways and molecular targets through which Apigenin exerts its action, notably involving cell cycle regulation, apoptosis induction, and stemness inhibition. H. H. Lee et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. explored the antitumor and anti-invasive effects of Apigenin on human breast carcinoma, focusing on its role in suppressing interleukin-6 (IL-6) expression. The study demonstrated that Apigenin significantly inhibited cell proliferation, migration, and invasion in breast cancer cell lines.</p><p id="Par8">PARP1 (poly [ADP-ribose] polymerase 1) is a key DNA damage repair enzyme that facilitates base excision repair and maintains genomic stability (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A). In breast cancer&#8212;particularly triple-negative subtypes&#8212;PARP1 overexpression supports tumor cell survival and therapy resistance, making it a prime target for PARP inhibitor therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. ESR1 is a ligand-activated transcription factor that drives proliferation and survival in hormone receptor&#8211;positive breast cancers. Mutations or overexpression of ESR1 contribute to endocrine therapy resistance and disease recurrence, underscoring its value as a prognostic biomarker and therapeutic target [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. However, there is research gap to study the molecular mechanism of both natural products from the prospective of computational approach. Furthermore, their synergistic mechanisms and precise molecular interactions remain underexplored.</p><p id="Par9">By prioritizing PARP1 and ESR1 through a systems-level filtering pipeline and linking their binding stability with tumor purity and CD8&#8314; T cell infiltration, this work provides a dual-target mechanistic insight for GNT and Apigenin that has not been reported previously. Additionally, the simultaneous prediction of pharmacokinetic and toxicity profiles alongside in vitro cytotoxic analysis offers a holistic preclinical assessment that bridges mechanistic understanding with translational potential.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Selection of compounds</title><p id="Par10">The 3D structure of both GNT and Apigenin were downloaded from PubChem (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>) in sdf format. The selection of GNT and Apigenin for this study was based on their well-documented anticancer properties, relevance in breast cancer, and potential for multitargeted therapy (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B). They modulate key oncogenic pathways (e.g., PI3K/AKT, NF-&#954;B, MAPK, and estrogen receptor signaling), making them promising candidates for multitargeted therapy. GNT modulates estrogen signaling and exhibits dose-dependent chemopreventive effects, while Apigenin, a non-estrogenic flavone, induces cell cycle arrest and apoptosis in hormone-independent breast cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Both compounds demonstrate low toxicity, making them promising candidates for adjuvant therapy. Furthermore, the pkCSM server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://biosig.lab.uq.edu.au/pkcsm/">https://biosig.lab.uq.edu.au/pkcsm/</ext-link>) was used for analysis of physicochemical, pharmacokinetic reports, and drug likeliness of GNT and Apigenin compounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. PerMM server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://permm.phar.umich.edu/">https://permm.phar.umich.edu/</ext-link>) was used for analysis of cell permeability and translocation pathways of GNT and Apigenin.</p><p id="Par11">
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><bold>A</bold>. Mechanistic pathways of Genistein and Apigenin with apoptosis activation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. HR = homologous recombination; PARP1 = poly [ADP-ribose] polymerase 1; ESR1 = estrogen receptor alpha. <bold>B</bold>. 2D structure of GNT and Apigenin</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e389" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40360_2025_1082_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Screening of targets associated with compounds</title><p id="Par12">The disease targets related to both GNT and Apigenin compounds were extracted from the SwissTargetPrediction web tool (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.swisstargetprediction.ch/">http://www.swisstargetprediction.ch/</ext-link>). The 3D structure of compounds was uploaded and <italic toggle="yes">Homo sapiens</italic> species was selected to get only human related targets. All the targets were included for study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Profiling of gene related to breast cancer</title><p id="Par13">The keyword selected for this study was &#8220;breast cancer,&#8221; and GeneCards<sup>&#174;</sup> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.genecards.org/">https://www.genecards.org/</ext-link>) was utilized to identify the genes associated with the progression of this disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Furthermore, an online program (Venny v2.1.0) was utilized to predict the collective genes that are commonly associated with this condition. The pseudogenes and uncategorized genes were excluded from the study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Establishing networks of protein&#8211;protein interactions (PPIs)</title><p id="Par14">A network was created from the Search Tool for the Retrieval of Interacting Genes/Proteins (STRING v12.0) database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://string-db.org/">https://string-db.org/</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. We specified &#8220;<italic toggle="yes">Homo sapiens</italic>&#8221; as the organism and established a confidence level of high confidence (0.70). To further investigate the biomolecular interactions among the relevant proteins, we constructed a PPI network utilizing Cytoscape software v3.10.2. We also determined the hub genes and top 10 best networked gene from the plugin (CytoHubba) option of Cytoscape software v3.10.2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Kyoto encyclopaedia of genes and genomes (KEGG) pathway study of enrichment and gene ontology (GO)</title><p id="Par15">The top 10 genes identified from Cytoscape v3.10.2 analysis were used for KEGG and Go enrichment analysis. We conducted enrichment analyses for GO and the KEGG using ShinyGo 0.82 server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bioinformatics.sdstate.edu/go/">https://bioinformatics.sdstate.edu/go/</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Both analyses resulted in an adjusted p-value of less than 0.05 (FDR cutoff) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Differential expression gene analysis and targets of breast cancer</title><p id="Par16">This study employed Gene Expression Profiling Interactive Analysis (GEPIA 2.0 ) to compare gene expression profiles in BRCA tissues against normal samples retrieved from the The Cancer Genome Atlas&#8221; (TCGA) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://portal.gdc.cancer.gov/">https://portal.gdc.cancer.gov/</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. We established thresholds of adjusted p-value &lt; 0.05 and |log<sub>2</sub> fold change (FC)| &gt; 1 to identify DEGs between tumor and normal groups. In the resulting visualization, lowly expressed genes were denoted by blue dots, whereas highly expressed genes were indicated by red dots. The focus of this analysis was &#8220;Breast cancer,&#8221; and gene cards were employed to pinpoint the gene targets associated with disease progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Expression patterns of PARP1 and ESR1 in various cancer types</title><p id="Par17">The expression patterns of PARP1 and ESR1 were analyzed using the Tumor Immune Estimation Resource TIMER v2.0 web server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://timer.cistrome.org/">http://timer.cistrome.org/</ext-link>). The analysis involved in putting the gene names PARP1 and ESR1 into the server&#8217;s gene expression analysis section, where data from various cancer types were selected. Results were visualized through scatter plots, bar charts, and heatmaps, allowing for the identification of correlations between PARP1 and ESR1 expression and immune cell infiltration, within the tumor microenvironment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Purity and infiltration analysis of T cell CD8&#8201;+&#8201;for hub genes PARP1 and ESR1</title><p id="Par18">Using the TIMER v2.0 web server, the purity and infiltration analysis of T cell CD8 + was conducted for the hub genes PARP1 and ESR1. The analysis began by accessing the TIMER v2.0 website and selecting the gene expression section, where PARP1 and ESR1 were input for evaluation across different cancer types. For each cancer type, the immune infiltration, specifically CD8 + T cell levels, and tumor purity were analyzed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Validation by molecular docking</title><p id="Par19">The 3D x-ray crystal structure of the targeted proteins, were obtained from the Protein Data Bank (PDB), with the respective entries identified as PDB ID: 6NRF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] and 7KBS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. These proteins were purified by eliminating water, heteroatoms, and various ligands using the BIOVIA Discovery Studio Visualizer 2021 software. To facilitate docking analysis in PyRx version 0.8, the protein structures were converted from PDB to PDBQT format [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. The grid parameters for the x, y, and z axes were defined and detailed in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. GNT and Apigenin were acquired in 3D format from the PubChem database and saved in SDF format. Additionally, the Open Babel tool within PyRx was employed to convert the files to PDBQT format, while energy minimization was conducted using the Merck Molecular Force Field (MMFF94) via Open Babel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. The docking results were visualized and analyzed with BIOVIA Discovery Studio Visualizer 2021 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].</p><p id="Par20">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Grid box coordinates of ligand protein interaction in Docking</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Apigenin-6NRF interaction</bold>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>GNT-7KBS interaction</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Exhaustiveness&#8201;=&#8201;8</p><p>center_x&#8201;=&#8201;24.384</p><p>center_y = -9.458</p><p>center_z&#8201;=&#8201;9.125</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Exhaustiveness&#8201;=&#8201;8</p><p>center_x = -2.367</p><p>center_y = -31.576</p><p>center_z&#8201;=&#8201;24.404</p></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Molecular docking protocol validation by redocking</title><p id="Par21">To validate the docking protocol, the co-crystallized ligand from each target structure was removed and redocked into the respective binding site using the same parameters. The root mean square deviation (RMSD) between the redocked pose and the experimental co-crystal pose was calculated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Molecular dynamic (MD) simulations</title><p id="Par22">MD simulations were conducted using the Desmond module of the Schr&#246;dinger Suite 2023-4 to evaluate the structural stability and dynamic behavior of the top docked complexes of GNT&#8211;ESR1 (PDB ID: 7KBS) and Apigenin&#8211;PARP1 (PDB ID: 6NRF). The protein&#8211;ligand complexes were first prepared using the Protein Preparation Wizard, which involved assigning bond orders, adding hydrogen atoms, and optimizing protonation states at physiological pH (7.0 &#177; 0.5). The systems were parameterized using the OPLS4 force field. Each complex was embedded in an orthorhombic simulation box and solvated with TIP3P water molecules, followed by the addition of Na&#8314; or Cl&#8315; ions to neutralize the system and mimic physiological ionic strength (0.15 M NaCl) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].</p><p id="Par23">The system was subjected to energy minimization using a combination of steepest descent and conjugate gradient methods to relieve any steric clashes. Subsequently, equilibration was carried out in two phases: first, a 1 ns NVT ensemble run was used to stabilize temperature, followed by a 1 ns NPT ensemble run to equilibrate the system pressure at 1 atm and temperature at 300 K, using the Berendsen thermostat and barostat. The production MD simulation was then run for 100 ns under NPT conditions, with temperature and pressure maintained at 300 K and 1 atm, respectively. Trajectory data were collected every 100 ps for analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Post-simulation analysis</title><p id="Par24">Post-simulation analyses included the calculation of RMSD to assess the overall stability of the protein and ligand, and Root Mean Square Fluctuation (RMSF) to evaluate residue-level flexibility. In addition, hydrogen bonding profiles, radius of gyration (Rg), and detailed protein&#8211;ligand interaction diagrams were generated using the Simulation Interaction Diagram tool in Desmond [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. To estimate binding free energy, the MM-GBSA (Molecular Mechanics-Generalized Born Surface Area) method was employed using the Prime module of Schr&#246;dinger. These analyses provided comprehensive insights into the binding stability and conformational dynamics of GNT and Apigenin within their respective targets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Cell lines and culture conditions</title><p id="Par25">HCC1937 human triple-negative breast cancer (TNBC) cells were obtained from the American Type Culture Collection (ATCC, Manassas, VA, USA; Cat. No. CRL-2336). Cell line identity was authenticated by short tandem repeat (STR) profiling and verified to be mycoplasma-free prior to use. Cells were maintained in RPMI-1640 medium (Gibco, Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA) supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum (FBS; Sigma-Aldrich, USA) and 1% Penicillin-Streptomycin (100 U/mL and 100 &#181;g/mL, Gibco). Cells were cultured at 37 &#176;C in a humidified incubator with 5% CO<sub>2</sub> and subcultured at ~ 75% confluence using 0.25% Trypsin-EDTA (Gibco) according to standard procedures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>MTT assay for cell viability and IC<sub>50</sub> determination</title><p id="Par26">HCC1937 cells were used to evaluate cytotoxicity by the MTT assay. Cells in exponential growth were trypsinized, counted, and seeded into 96-well plates at 5 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup> cells per well in complete growth medium and allowed to adhere overnight at 37 &#176;C in a humidified 5% CO&#8322; atmosphere. Stock solutions of GNT and Apigenin were prepared in DMSO and diluted in culture medium to give final treatment concentrations ranging from 10 to 400 &#181;M (final DMSO concentration &#8804; 0.1% v/v) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. After adhesion, cells were exposed to serially diluted compounds (six technical replicates per concentration) for 48 h. At the end of treatment, 20 &#181;L of MTT solution (5 mg/mL in PBS) was added to each well and plates were incubated for 3&#8211;4 h at 37 &#176;C to allow formation of formazan crystals. The medium was then removed and formazan was dissolved by adding 100 &#181;L of DMSO per well with gentle shaking for 10&#8211;15 min. Negative controls included untreated cells and vehicle control wells containing 0.1% DMSO. 5-Fluorouracil (5-FU) served as a positive control to verify responsiveness and compare cytotoxic potency. Absorbance was measured at 570 nm with a 630 nm reference on a microplate reader [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Percentage cell viability was calculated relative to vehicle control wells, and dose&#8211;response curves were constructed from mean &#177; SD of six replicates. IC<sub>50</sub> value was determined by nonlinear regression of the log-transformed concentrations using a four-parameter sigmoidal model (GraphPad Prism v10). All experiments included untreated and vehicle controls were repeated independently at least twice to ensure reproducibility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Toxicity prediction</title><p id="Par27">Toxicity prediction for GNT and Apigenin was performed using the pkCSM online server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://biosig.lab.uq.edu.au/pkcsm/">https://biosig.lab.uq.edu.au/pkcsm/</ext-link>). The SMILES structures of both compounds were retrieved from PubChem and input into the pkCSM interface. The results provided a comprehensive toxicity profile, supporting the safety potential of both compounds for further pharmacological evaluation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec19"><title>Screening of GNT and apigenin characteristics</title><p id="Par28">Apigenin and GNT exhibit favorable drug-like properties in accordance with Lipinski&#8217;s Rule of Five (Supplementary file, Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Both compounds have a molecular weight of 270.24&#160;g/mol, LogP of 2.58, one rotatable bond, five hydrogen bond acceptors, and three hydrogen bond donors. Their polar surface area (112.52 &#197;&#178;) also supports good oral bioavailability, indicating potential suitability as orally active therapeutic agents.</p><p id="Par29">Both Apigenin and GNT demonstrated favorable pharmacokinetic profiles. They exhibited high predicted intestinal absorption (&gt;&#8201;93%) and moderate Caco-2 permeability, indicating good potential for oral bioavailability. While both acted as P-glycoprotein substrates, they were not inhibitors of P-gp I or II, suggesting a low risk of transporter-mediated drug interactions. Their predicted blood&#8211;brain barrier (BBB) permeability and CNS penetration were low, implying limited central nervous system exposure. Neither compound was identified as a substrate for CYP2D6 or CYP3A4, though both were predicted to inhibit CYP1A2 and CYP2C19, indicating possible metabolic interactions (Supplementary file, Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). The predicted total clearance was moderate, with Apigenin showing a slightly higher rate than GNT. Additionally, both compounds were not substrates of renal OCT2, suggesting minimal involvement in renal transporter-mediated elimination. These findings supported the drug-likeness and systemic safety potential of both phytochemicals.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Cell permeability analysis</title><p id="Par30">Cell permeability assessments revealed that both GNT and Apigenin exhibited moderate membrane permeability across various biological models. GNT showed a free energy of binding to DOPC bilayer of &#8722;&#8201;2.86&#160;kcal/mol, while Apigenin had a slightly less favorable value of &#8722;&#8201;2.18&#160;kcal/mol, indicating lower membrane affinity. The log permeability coefficients (Po) for both compounds across different models&#8212;including BLM, BBB, Caco-2, and PAMPA-DS&#8212;ranged from &#8722;&#8201;4.91 to &#8722;&#8201;6.57, with Apigenin consistently displaying marginally lower permeability than GNT (Supplementary file, Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). These values suggested that both compounds were capable of passive diffusion, though with relatively low permeability, particularly across the PAMPA-DS model, which mimics the gastrointestinal tract (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par31">
<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Cell permeability representation of translocation pathway of GNT and Apigenin</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e645" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40360_2025_1082_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Differential expression gene analysis and targets of breast cancer</title><p id="Par32">A total of 3,556 DEGs were identified between breast cancer and normal tissues, with 2,138 genes significantly downregulated and 1,418 genes upregulated based on the criteria of adjusted p-value&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05 and |log<sub>2</sub> fold change| &gt; 1.</p><p id="Par33">Figure&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A illustrates the chromosomal distribution of DEGs mapped across all chromosomes, based on GRCh38.p2 annotation. Both overexpressed (red) and under expressed (green) genes were distributed broadly across multiple chromosomes, with noticeable clustering in chromosomes 1, 17, and 19, indicating hotspots of transcriptomic dysregulation in breast cancer. Figure&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B presents a volcano plot showing the magnitude and significance of gene expression changes. Notably, several hub genes previously identified through network analysis were also differentially expressed. Among these, PARP1, AURKB, PLK1, MMP9, and ESR1 were significantly upregulated, whereas EGFR, ABCB1, MET, KDR, and PTGS2 were markedly downregulated. These genes are known to play critical roles in cell proliferation, apoptosis, DNA repair, and drug resistance, further validating their relevance in breast cancer pathogenesis and therapeutic targeting.</p><p id="Par34">
<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Chromosomal distribution of differentially expressed genes (DEGs) in breast cancer, based on GRCh38.p2 (NCBI) (<bold>A</bold>). Volcano plot illustrating the log<sub>2</sub> fold change versus &#8211;log<sub>10</sub>(p-value) for gene expression in breast cancer samples (<bold>B</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e680" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40360_2025_1082_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Targets of apigenin and GNT</title><p id="Par35">For GNT (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A), the major predicted targets were nuclear receptors (26.7%) and family A G protein-coupled receptors (26.7%), followed by a range of other classes, including enzymes, kinases, oxidoreductases, cytochrome P450s, and hydrolases, each representing 6.7% of targets. For Apigenin (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B), predicted targets were more evenly distributed, with prominent involvement of oxidoreductases (20%), kinases (20%), and enzymes (13.3%), indicating a broader interaction profile. Additionally, Apigenin targeted cytochrome P450s, nuclear receptors, and GPCRs, each accounting for 6.7&#8211;13.3% of its predicted interactions.</p><p id="Par36">
<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Predicted target class distribution of GNT (<bold>A</bold>) and Apigenin (<bold>B</bold>). GNT predominantly targets nuclear receptors and family A G protein&#8211;coupled receptors (26.7% each), whereas Apigenin shows a broader distribution, with major associations to oxidoreductases, kinases, and enzymes (20% each)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e707" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40360_2025_1082_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Screening of therapeutic targets in breast cancer</title><p id="Par37">The network analysis identified a total of 10 nodes and 32 edges, resulting in an average node degree of 6.4. This finding indicates a substantial level of interconnectivity among the target genes (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>A). The average local clustering coefficient was computed at 0.909, suggesting a tightly clustered network in which genes are likely to engage in interactions with one another. Notably, although the expected number of edges was 12, the observed count significantly surpassed this, thereby reinforcing the conclusion that the interactions are non-random. This assertion is further validated by the PPI enrichment p-value of 5.52&#8201;&#215;&#8201;10&#8315;&#8311;, signifying that the identified interactions hold statistical significance and biological relevance. The analysis integrated predicted gene targets of GNT and Apigenin with breast cancer-associated genes and DEGs. These intersecting genes likely represent the core pharmacological targets through which both phytochemicals exert anticancer effects.</p><p id="Par38">
<fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Venn diagram showing the overlap of predicted gene targets for GNT, Apigenin, breast cancer-related genes, and differentially expressed genes (DEGs) (<bold>A</bold>). A total of 10 common genes were identified at the intersection of all four datasets, representing potential therapeutic targets. PPI network of the 10 intersecting genes constructed using the STRING database (<bold>B</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e731" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40360_2025_1082_Fig5_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>PPI network</title><p id="Par39">The resulting network demonstrated a high degree of connectivity, with prominent hub nodes including PARP1, ESR1, EGFR, MMP9, and ABCB1 (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>B; Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). These genes are known to be critically involved in pathways regulating DNA repair, hormone signalling, cell proliferation, and drug resistance. The presence of these genes in the PPI core supports their central role in breast cancer progression and underscores their potential as key intervention points for GNT and Apigenin (Figs.&#160;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>A, &amp; <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>B).</p><p id="Par40">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Target genes selection for further molecular interaction analysis based on degree methods</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rank</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Name</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PARP1</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ESR1</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MET</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ABCB1</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KDR</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PTGS2</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MMP9</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PLK1</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par41">
<fig id="Fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Hub gene ranking of overlapping target genes associated with GNT, Apigenin, and breast cancer, generated using the CytoHubba plugin in Cytoscape</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e844" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40360_2025_1082_Fig6_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par42">
<fig id="Fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Compound&#8211;target interaction network showing the relationship between GNT, Apigenin, and the top 10 hub genes identified in breast cancer (<bold>A</bold>). Arrows indicate the predicted regulatory interactions between the phytochemicals and target genes, highlighting shared and unique targets. Compound&#8211;target&#8211;pathway network constructed using KEGG pathway enrichment analysis (<bold>B</bold>). The diagram illustrates how GNT and Apigenin modulate key signalling pathways through their interaction with hub genes</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e861" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40360_2025_1082_Fig7_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>KEGG pathway</title><p id="Par43">KEGG enrichment analysis revealed several significantly enriched pathways, with the most breast cancer&#8211;relevant being the estrogen signaling pathway, endocrine resistance, and EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitor resistance. These pathways directly correspond to the identified hub targets ESR1 and PARP1, linking GNT to estrogen receptor regulation and Apigenin to DNA repair inhibition. Additionally, enrichment of the PI3K&#8211;Akt and MAPK signaling pathways suggests broader involvement in proliferation and survival cascades frequently dysregulated in breast cancer. Other pathways, such as microRNAs in cancer, further support the regulation of gene expression and resistance mechanisms (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). Ancillary pathways (e.g., gastric cancer, focal adhesion) were identified but appear secondary in relevance and are provided in Supplementary data (Tables <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>).</p><p id="Par44">
<fig id="Fig8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Bar plot of KEGG pathway enrichment analysis for common target genes of GNT and Apigenin in breast cancer. The x-axis represents fold enrichment, and the color gradient reflects the &#8211;log<sub>10</sub>(FDR), indicating the statistical significance of enrichment</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e887" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40360_2025_1082_Fig8_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par45">Among the top three enriched pathways, the EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitor resistance pathway (Path: hsa01521) exhibited the most significant enrichment, reporting an FDR of 0.0001. This pathway encompasses 79 genes and displays a fold enrichment of 86.89. Critical genes implicated in this pathway include EGFR, KDR, and MET, underscoring their essential roles in mechanisms of resistance. Key genes identified within this pathway include EGFR, MET, MMP9, ABCB1, and PTGS2, emphasizing the multifaceted regulatory role of microRNAs in oncogenic processes and treatment resistance (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><p id="Par46">
<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Enrichment FDR, fold enrichment and pathway of target genes in KEGG pathway</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Enrichment FDR</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pathway Genes</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fold Enrichment</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pathway</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Genes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0001</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">79</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86.88987</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Path: hsa01521 EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitor resistance</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR, KDR, MET</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00014</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.25579</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Path: hsa01522 Endocrine resistance</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR, ESR1, MMP9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.41E-07</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">161</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71.05901</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Path: hsa05206 MicroRNAs in cancer</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR, MET, MMP9, ABCB1, PTGS2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.34E-07</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">202</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.63614</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Path: hsa05205 Proteoglycans in cancer</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR, ESR1, KDR, MET, MMP9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000358</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">138</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49.7413</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Path: hsa04915 Estrogen signaling pathway</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR, ESR1, MMP9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000378</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">148</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.38041</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Path: hsa05226 Gastric cancer</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR, MET, ABCB1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000811</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">200</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.3215</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Path: hsa04510 Focal adhesion</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR, KDR, MET</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000833</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">210</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.68714</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Path: hsa04015 Rap1 signalling pathway</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR, KDR, MET</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001001</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">235</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.20979</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Path: hsa04014 Ras signalling pathway</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR, KDR, MET</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.29E-05</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">530</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.58585</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Path: hsa05200 Pathways in cancer</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EGFR, ESR1, MET, MMP9, PTGS2</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>GO enrichment analysis</title><p id="Par47">In the biological process category, the enriched terms &#8220;regulation of apoptosis,&#8221; &#8220;response to UV,&#8221; and &#8220;positive regulation of phosphorylation&#8221; highlight the role of PARP1 and ESR1 in DNA damage response and survival signaling (Figs.&#160;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>A-C). In the molecular function category, significant enrichment was noted in &#8220;kinase activity&#8221; and &#8220;transmembrane receptor protein tyrosine kinase activity,&#8221; consistent with modulation of growth factor signaling. The cellular component analysis revealed enrichment in the &#8220;chromosome passenger complex&#8221; and &#8220;spindle midzone,&#8221; supporting roles in mitotic control.</p><p id="Par48">
<fig id="Fig9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Gene ontology association mechanism interaction in different pathways of target genes. Where (<bold>A</bold>) represents biological process, (<bold>B</bold>) represents Cellular components and (<bold>C</bold>) represents Molecular functions</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1056" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40360_2025_1082_Fig9_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Expression patterns of PARP1 and ESR1 analysis</title><p id="Par49">As shown in Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>A, PARP1 expression was significantly upregulated in multiple tumor types, including breast cancer (BRCA), lung adenocarcinoma (LUAD), esophageal carcinoma (ESCA), and glioblastoma multiforme (GBM), compared to their normal tissue counterparts (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001). In breast cancer specifically, PARP1 exhibited elevated expression across subtypes, suggesting its broad involvement in DNA damage repair and tumor cell survival mechanisms. In contrast, Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>B illustrates that ESR1 expression was more variable across cancer types. Notably, high ESR1 expression was observed in breast cancer, particularly in luminal subtypes, reinforcing its role as a classical estrogen receptor and prognostic biomarker. However, ESR1 expression was significantly downregulated in tumors such as cholangiocarcinoma (CHOL), head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSC), and lung squamous cell carcinoma (LUSC). The subtype-specific expression of ESR1 supports its potential as a personalized therapeutic target, particularly in hormone-responsive breast cancers.</p><p id="Par50">
<fig id="Fig10" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Box plot showing the expression levels of PARP1 across various tumor types compared to corresponding normal tissues, based on TCGA data using GEPIA2 (<bold>A</bold>). Box plot representing the expression distribution of ESR1 across different cancer types and normal tissues (<bold>B</bold>). ESR1 showed elevated expression in hormone-responsive cancers such as breast cancer but was downregulated in several others. Red dots represent tumor samples, while blue dots represent normal tissues</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1086" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40360_2025_1082_Fig10_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>Purity and infiltration analysis of T cell CD8&#8201;+&#8201;of hub genes PARP1 and ESR1 analysis</title><p id="Par51">For the PARP1 gene, a weak positive correlation with tumor purity was identified (Spearman&#8217;s &#961;&#8201;=&#8201;0.063, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0459) (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>A-B). This indicates a minimal association between PARP1 expression and the proportion of tumor cells in the tissue. Conversely, PARP1 expression showed a weak but statistically significant negative correlation with CD8&#8201;+&#8201;T cell infiltration (&#961; = &#8722;&#8201;0.129, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;4.58e&#8211;05). This suggests that higher levels of PARP1 expression may be associated with a decreased presence of cytotoxic immune cells in the tumor microenvironment. In contrast, the ESR1 gene displayed a moderate positive correlation with tumor purity (&#961;&#8201;=&#8201;0.222, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1.31e&#8211;12), indicating that ESR1 is predominantly expressed by tumor cells in breast cancer tissues. Additionally, ESR1 had a weak positive correlation with CD8&#8201;+&#8201;T cell infiltration (&#961;&#8201;=&#8201;0.088, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;5.52e&#8211;03), suggesting a slight association between ESR1 expression and the presence of immune cells. These findings reveal distinct patterns of association between gene expression and various factors in the tumor microenvironment. PARP1 appears to be linked with immune exclusion, while ESR1 reflects a stronger tumor-specific expression with limited interaction with immune cells.</p><p id="Par52">
<fig id="Fig11" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>Correlation of PARP1 expression with tumor purity (left) and CD8&#8314; T cell infiltration (right) in breast cancer (BRCA), analyzed using TIMER2.0 (<bold>A</bold>). A weak but statistically significant positive correlation was observed between PARP1 and CD8&#8314; T cell infiltration (Rho&#8201;=&#8201;0.129, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;4.58e&#8211;05). Correlation of ESR1 expression with tumor purity (left) and CD8&#8314; T cell infiltration (right) (B). ESR1 showed a moderate positive correlation with tumor purity (Rho&#8201;=&#8201;0.222, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1.31e&#8211;12) and a weaker but significant correlation with CD8&#8314; T cell infiltration (Rho&#8201;=&#8201;0.088, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;5.52e&#8211;03). Blue lines represent the trend lines of the correlation, with shaded areas indicating the confidence interval</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1128" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40360_2025_1082_Fig11_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec29"><title>Molecular docking analysis</title><p id="Par53">The molecular docking analysis of GNT and Apigenin against the PARP1 (PDB ID: 6NRF) and ESR1 (PDB ID: 7KBS) proteins demonstrates significant binding affinities and interaction profiles that highlight their potential utility as therapeutic agents. For the PARP1 protein, Apigenin exhibits a superior binding affinity of -9.6&#160;kcal/mol, in contrast to GNT, which showed a binding affinity of -8.1&#160;kcal/mol (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). GNT, a ligand interacting with ESR1, establishes several conventional hydrogen bonds with specific amino acid residues, notably HIS A:524, ARG A:394, and LEU A:387 (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>A &amp; B). These hydrogen bonds, indicated by green dashed lines, signify robust polar interactions that are instrumental in anchoring the ligand within the binding site. Moreover, the aromatic rings of the ligand participate in &#960;&#8211;&#960; T-shaped interactions with PHE A:404 and &#960;&#8211;sigma interactions with LEU A:525. These interactions contribute to the ligand&#8217;s orientation within the hydrophobic pocket through stacking and electron cloud interactions. Additionally, the strength of hydrophobic interactions is augmented by multiple &#960;&#8211;alkyl contacts with residues such as LEU A:346, ALA A:350, LEU A:391, and LEU A:387, as illustrated in light violet (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). These non-polar residues create an environment that complements the aromatic systems of the ligand, thereby enhancing its binding stability. The 2D interaction diagram of the PARP1-Apigenin complex reveals that Apigenin establishes two conventional hydrogen bonds with residues GLU988 and GLY863, exhibiting bond lengths of 2.43 &#197; and 2.76 &#197;, respectively (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>C &amp; D). Moreover, &#960;-&#960; stacking interactions are noted with residues HIS862 and TYR907, enhancing stability and specificity within the active site.</p><p id="Par54">
<table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Binding score (Kcal/mol) of ligands -protein complex interaction</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Targets</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Binding score</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GNT</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Apigenin</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PARP1(6NRF)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-8.1 Kcal/mol</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-9.6 Kcal/mol</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ESR1 (7KBS)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-8.3 Kcal/mol</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-7.7 Kcal/mol</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par55">
<table-wrap id="Tab5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Ligand - protein interaction of GNT-ESR1 and Apigenin- PARP1 complex</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Type of Interaction</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Amino Acid Residue (Chain: Position)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Distance (&#197;)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">GNT-ESR1 complex</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Conventional Hydrogen Bond</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>HIS A:524</p><p>ARG A:394</p><p>LEU A:387</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.02</p><p>2.30, 2.54</p><p>2.14</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pi&#8211;Pi T-shaped</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PHE A:404</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.75, 4.91, 4.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pi&#8211;Sigma</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LEU A:525</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pi&#8211;Alkyl</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>LEU A:346</p><p>ALA A:350</p><p>LEU A:391</p><p>LEU A:387</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>5.01</p><p>5.18</p><p>4.96</p><p>4.75</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Apigenin- PARP1 complex</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Conventional Hydrogen Bond</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>GLU A:988</p><p>GLY A:863</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>2.43</p><p>2.07, 2.76</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pi&#8211;Pi Stacked</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>TYR A:907</p><p>HIS A:862</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>4.09</p><p>4.57, 6.00</p></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par56">
<fig id="Fig12" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 12</label><caption><p>Molecular docking interactions of GNT and Apigenin with ESR1 and PARP1. Three-dimensional (<bold>A</bold>) and two-dimensional (<bold>B</bold>) interaction diagrams of the GNT&#8211;ESR1 complex, showing key hydrogen bonds with HIS524, ARG394, and LEU387, along with &#960;&#8211;&#960; and hydrophobic contacts stabilizing the ligand within the binding pocket. Three-dimensional (<bold>C</bold>) and two-dimensional (<bold>D</bold>) interaction diagrams of the Apigenin&#8211;PARP1 complex, illustrating hydrogen bonds with GLU988 and GLY863, and &#960;&#8211;&#960; stacking interactions with TYR907 and HIS862. These interactions highlight the strong and stable binding orientations of both compounds within their respective active sites</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1289" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40360_2025_1082_Fig12_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par57">
<fig id="Fig13" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 13</label><caption><p>Docking Protocol Validation for PARP1 and ESR1. (<bold>A</bold>) Superimposition of the native co-crystallized ligand (yellow) and the redocked ligand (blue) in the ESR1 active site. (<bold>B</bold>) Superimposition of the native co-crystallized ligand (grey) and the redocked ligand (purple) in the PARP1 binding pocket</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1306" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40360_2025_1082_Fig13_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par58">The docking protocol demonstrated satisfactory reliability, as the redocking of native ligands yielded RMSD values of 1.72 &#197; (PARP1) and 1.89 &#197; (ESR1), indicating accurate reproduction of the experimentally observed binding poses (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig13" ref-type="fig">13</xref>A-B).</p></sec><sec id="Sec30"><title>MD simulation</title><p id="Par59">To evaluate the structural stability and dynamic behavior of the Apigenin&#8211;PARP1 complex, a 100 ns MD simulation was conducted, and several parameters were analyzed (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig14" ref-type="fig">14</xref>A&#8211;D). Figure&#160;<xref rid="Fig13" ref-type="fig">13</xref>A shows the RMSD plot of the PARP1 protein backbone (green) and the ligand Apigenin (pink). The protein RMSD increased gradually and stabilized after ~&#8201;40 ns, indicating a well-equilibrated system. The ligand RMSD remained consistently low throughout the simulation (&lt;&#8201;3&#197;), suggesting that Apigenin maintained a stable binding conformation within the active site of PARP1. Figure&#160;<xref rid="Fig14" ref-type="fig">14</xref>B presents the RMSF of protein residues, where most residues displayed minimal fluctuation (&lt;&#8201;2 &#197;), indicating structural rigidity. A few regions&#8212;particularly around residue index&#8201;~&#8201;150&#8212;exhibited higher flexibility, possibly corresponding to loop or solvent-exposed regions. No significant fluctuation was observed in the binding site, supporting the stability of the ligand&#8211;protein interaction. Figure&#160;<xref rid="Fig14" ref-type="fig">14</xref>C illustrates the RMSF of the ligand atoms, confirming low internal fluctuation. Atoms indexed 12 to 18 showed slightly higher deviations, which may reflect minor rotational flexibility of side groups, but overall, the ligand retained a compact and stable structure. Figure&#160;<xref rid="Fig14" ref-type="fig">14</xref>D displays the torsional angle distribution of Apigenin. The consistent periodicity and narrow angle distribution observed in the plots suggest limited conformational changes in the ligand, further supporting its stable orientation within the binding pocket throughout the simulation.</p><p id="Par60">
<fig id="Fig14" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 14</label><caption><p>RMSD of Apigenin- PARP1 complex (<bold>A</bold>), RMSF of protein (<bold>B</bold>), RMSF of ligand (<bold>C</bold>), and torsional angle (<bold>D</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1353" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40360_2025_1082_Fig14_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par61">Figure&#160;<xref rid="Fig15" ref-type="fig">15</xref>A presents the interaction fraction histogram, which highlights the frequency and type of contacts between Apigenin and specific PARP1 residues. Notably, GLY-863, PHE-897, TYR-907, and TYR-989 exhibited the highest interaction fractions, indicating persistent and strong binding throughout the simulation. The interaction types included hydrogen bonding (green), hydrophobic contacts (blue), water bridges (purple), and ionic interactions (light blue), with hydrophobic and water-mediated contacts being dominant.</p><p id="Par62">
<fig id="Fig15" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 15</label><caption><p>Apigenin - PARP1 complex contacts histogram (<bold>A</bold>) and timeline (<bold>B</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1375" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40360_2025_1082_Fig15_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par63">Figure&#160;<xref rid="Fig15" ref-type="fig">15</xref>B shows the interaction timeline map, indicating the temporal stability of these contacts. The top panel displays the total number of interactions maintained at each frame, with a consistent average of 6&#8211;10 contacts across the simulation time, signifying stable ligand engagement. The heat map below shows that residues such as TYR-989, GLU-988, PHE-897, and SER-904 maintained frequent contacts with Apigenin over time, confirming their key role in stabilizing the complex.</p></sec><sec id="Sec31"><title>FEL and PCA</title><p id="Par64">The FEL and PCA analyses revealed multiple low-energy basins and two dominant conformational clusters, indicating a dynamically sampled but overall stable Apigenin&#8211;PARP1 complex. Bimodal PC distributions and broader PC1 variability reflect structural flexibility with a consistently favored stable conformational state (Supplementary file, Figs.&#160;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1S</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2S</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec32"><title>MM/GBSA energy calculation</title><p id="Par65">Figure&#160;<xref rid="Fig16" ref-type="fig">16</xref> presents a box plot of MM-GBSA energy components, highlighting the contributions of various interaction types to the total binding free energy (&#916;G_bind). The average &#916;G_bind was approximately &#8722;&#8201;74.96&#160;kcal/mol, indicating strong binding affinity. Among the components, van der Waals, Coulombic, and lipophilic interactions were the dominant stabilizing forces. Hydrogen bonding and covalent contributions were smaller but consistent across the trajectory. The mean Coulombic energy was approximately &#8722;&#8201;20.36&#160;kcal/mol, and the van der Waals contribution was around &#8722;&#8201;49.91&#160;kcal/mol, supporting the non-covalent nature of Apigenin&#8217;s stable association with the PARP1 active site.</p><p id="Par66">
<fig id="Fig16" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 16</label><caption><p>MM-GBSA energy analysis of the Apigenin - PARP1 complex during molecular dynamics simulation</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1407" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40360_2025_1082_Fig16_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec33"><title>Cytotoxic study by MTT assay</title><p id="Par67">The cytotoxic effects of GNT and Apigenin on HCC1937 cells were evaluated using the MTT assay, and the results are presented in Fig. <xref rid="Fig17" ref-type="fig">17</xref>A &amp; B. Both compounds exhibited a concentration-dependent decrease in cell viability. The dose&#8211;response curves revealed a typical sigmoidal pattern, with GNT displaying a slightly greater inhibitory effect compared to Apigenin. The calculated IC<sub>50</sub> values were 67.01 &#177; 1.67 &#181;M for GNT and 70.24 &#177; 1.45 &#181;M for Apigenin, indicating that the two flavonoids exhibit comparable cytotoxic activity under the tested conditions. The positive control, 5-FU, showed an IC<sub>50</sub> of 25.94 &#177; 1.12 &#181;M in HCC1937 cells, as reported by D. Jha et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Bar graph analysis further supported these findings, showing that at lower concentrations (10&#8211;40 &#181;M), cell viability remained above 90%, whereas concentrations above 60 &#181;M caused a significant reduction in viability, dropping below 50% at higher doses (&#8805; 100 &#181;M). These results suggest that both flavonoids exert dose-dependent antiproliferative effects on HCC1937 cells.</p><p id="Par68">
<fig id="Fig17" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 17</label><caption><p>Dose-dependent cytotoxic effects of GNT and Apigenin on HCC1937 cells evaluated by the MTT assay. (<bold>A</bold>) Dose&#8211;response curves showing percentage cell viability plotted against the logarithm of compound concentration (&#181;M). (<bold>B</bold>) Bar graph representation of cell viability at increasing concentrations (10&#8211;400 &#181;M) compared to control. Data are presented as mean&#8201;&#177;&#8201;SD (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;6)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1441" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="40360_2025_1082_Fig17_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec34"><title>Toxicity analysis</title><p id="Par69">The toxicity profiles of Apigenin and GNT were evaluated to assess their safety for potential therapeutic use. Both compounds were predicted to be non-hepatotoxic and non-sensitizing to skin, indicating a favorable safety margin for systemic and topical exposure. The maximum tolerated dose (MTD) in humans was slightly higher for GNT (0.478 log mg/kg/day) compared to Apigenin (0.328 log mg/kg/day), suggesting that GNT may be better tolerated at higher doses. Regarding acute toxicity, oral rat LD<sub>50</sub> values were within a comparable range for both compounds, with Apigenin at 2.45&#160;mol/kg and GNT at 2.268&#160;mol/kg, indicating low acute toxicity. The chronic toxicity values, represented by the LOAEL, were also similar: 2.298 log mg/kg/day for Apigenin and 2.189 log mg/kg/day for GNT. Furthermore, both compounds tested negative for AMES toxicity, suggesting they were non-mutagenic (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>).</p><p id="Par70">
<table-wrap id="Tab6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Toxicity reports of apigenin and GNT</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AMES Toxicity</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Categorical (Yes/No)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<bold>Apigenin</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Max. tolerated dose (human)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.328</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Numeric (log mg/kg/day)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Oral Rat Acute Toxicity (LD<sub>50</sub>)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Numeric (mol/kg)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Oral Rat Chronic Toxicity (LOAEL)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.298</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Numeric (log mg/kg/day)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hepatotoxicity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Categorical (Yes/No)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Skin Sensitisation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Categorical (Yes/No)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<bold>GNT</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Max. tolerated dose (human)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.478</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Numeric (log mg/kg/day)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Oral Rat Acute Toxicity (LD<sub>50</sub>)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.268</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Numeric (mol/kg)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Oral Rat Chronic Toxicity (LOAEL)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.189</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Numeric (log mg/kg/day)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hepatotoxicity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Categorical (Yes/No)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Skin Sensitisation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Categorical (Yes/No)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec35"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par71">Breast cancer remains a leading cause of cancer-related mortality among women worldwide, highlighting the urgent need for novel and safer therapeutic agents. In this study, we employed an integrative in silico approach combining network pharmacology, onco-omics profiling, molecular docking, and MD simulations to evaluate the anticancer potential of two polyphenols&#8212;GNT and Apigenin&#8212;against key molecular targets in breast cancer. Through network pharmacology, gene expression analysis, molecular docking, and MD simulation, we identified PARP1 and ESR1 as key hub targets modulated by these phytochemicals. Network pharmacology represents a contemporary analytical methodology that facilitates the systematic examination of drugs and diseases through multitarget and multipath frameworks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. The integration of network pharmacology with molecular docking provides a synergistic platform for elucidating the therapeutic potential of phytochemicals, specifically GNT and Apigenin, in the context of breast cancer. Such an integrative analysis allows for a deeper understanding of the multifaceted relationships between bioactive molecules and their biological targets, thus facilitating the prediction of therapeutic targets and key signalling pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>].</p><p id="Par72">Our findings are consistent with and extend the existing body of literature on the anticancer mechanisms of GNT and Apigenin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. GNT and Apigenin were selected based on published evidence demonstrating their potent anti-proliferative and pro-apoptotic activities in breast cancer, including in hormone receptor&#8211;negative and chemoresistant phenotypes. Both belong to the flavonoid class of polyphenols and have been shown to modulate key oncogenic targets involved in breast cancer progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>], including ESR1 and PARP1, which were identified as central nodes in our preliminary network analysis. Additionally, their established safety profile and clinical relevance as nutraceutical compounds further support their selection for focused investigation in this study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>].</p><p id="Par73">ESR1 and PARP1 targets are well-documented in the literature for their functional roles in breast cancer progression. PARP1, a key player in DNA damage repair and genomic stability, is particularly relevant in TNBC where its inhibition has shown clinical benefit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. ESR1, on the other hand, is a hallmark of hormone-responsive breast cancers and remains a critical prognostic and therapeutic marker [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. These findings underscore the clinical relevance of both targets and justify their selection for downstream interaction studies.</p><p id="Par74">Previous studies have demonstrated that GNT exerts its anticancer effects through modulation of estrogen receptors, induction of apoptosis, and inhibition of tyrosine kinases and angiogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. In particular, its affinity for ESR1 has been documented in hormone-dependent breast cancer models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. Our docking and MD results reinforce these findings by showing stable and energetically favorable binding of GNT to ESR1, supported by persistent hydrogen bonding and low RMSD values. Moreover, GEPIA2 expression analysis revealed high ESR1 expression in luminal breast cancer subtypes, corroborating its role as a therapeutically relevant target. Similarly, Apigenin has been shown to inhibit proliferation, induce apoptosis, and target breast cancer stem-like cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. In our study, Apigenin exhibited a strong binding affinity to PARP1, a key DNA repair enzyme that is overexpressed in triple-negative breast cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. The favorable binding energy and stable contact profile throughout the MD simulation underscore its potential as a PARP1 inhibitor. Importantly, MM-GBSA binding free energy calculations indicated that van der Waals, Coulombic, and lipophilic interactions were the primary contributors to binding stability, with Apigenin&#8211;PARP1 exhibiting a highly favorable binding energy of approximately &#8722; 74.96 kcal/mol. Contact frequency analysis further highlighted key interactions with residues such as TYR-989, GLU-988, and PHE-897, which remained consistent throughout the simulation.</p><p id="Par75">The KEGG and GO enrichment analyses provide mechanistic insight into how GNT and Apigenin interact with critical oncogenic pathways in breast cancer. Enrichment of the estrogen signaling and endocrine resistance pathways strongly supports GNT&#8217;s activity against ESR1, consistent with its known phytoestrogenic properties and its ability to modulate estrogen-driven tumor proliferation. Importantly, these pathways are central to hormone-responsive breast cancers, where resistance to endocrine therapy remains a major clinical challenge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. Furthermore, Apigenin&#8217;s preferential binding to PARP1 aligns with enrichment of DNA repair and resistance-related pathways, highlighting its potential role as a PARP1 inhibitor, particularly relevant for TNBC that lack hormone receptors but are dependent on DNA damage repair mechanisms. The PI3K&#8211;Akt and MAPK signaling pathways, enriched in both compounds, further underscore their multi-targeted ability to regulate survival and proliferation cascades beyond hormone signaling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. Additionally, enrichment of microRNAs in cancer suggests that these flavonoids may indirectly influence post-transcriptional gene regulation, adding another layer of mechanistic complexity. While several additional pathways were enriched (e.g., focal adhesion, proteoglycans in cancer), these appear to play supportive roles and were therefore considered secondary. The pkCSM toxicity and ADMET predictions supported the safety and drug-likeness of both compounds, with no hepatotoxicity or mutagenic potential and favorable absorption profiles. These results align with previous findings showing that GNT and Apigenin exhibit low systemic toxicity and good tolerability in preclinical models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>].</p><p id="Par76">The FEL analysis revealed multiple low-energy basins with a dominant, deeply populated conformational state, indicating that the Apigenin&#8211;PARP1 complex preferentially adopts highly stable binding poses during the simulation. This suggests that once Apigenin is accommodated within the PARP1 active site, it requires minimal conformational rearrangements to maintain energetically favorable interactions, an important feature for sustained inhibitory activity in vivo. The presence of smaller, higher-energy states reflects the natural flexibility of the complex, allowing it to adapt to subtle structural fluctuations without destabilizing the binding interface.</p><p id="Par77">The MTT assay revealed that GNT and Apigenin inhibited HCC1937 breast cancer cell viability in a dose-dependent manner, with IC<sub>50</sub> values of 67.01 &#177; 1.67 &#181;M and 70.24 &#177; 1.45 &#181;M, respectively. These findings are consistent with earlier reports showing GNT exerting cytotoxic effects in MCF-7 cells (IC<sub>50</sub> ~ 40&#8211;60 &#181;M) and TNBC lines such as MDA-MB-231 (IC<sub>50</sub> ~ 60&#8211;100 &#181;M) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. Similarly, Apigenin has demonstrated growth inhibition in breast cancer models, with IC<sub>50</sub> values typically ranging between 50 and 80 &#181;M [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]. The slightly higher potency of GNT in our study correlates with its stronger affinity for ESR1 observed in docking and MD simulations, while Apigenin&#8217;s cytotoxicity aligns with its PARP1 inhibition. Mechanistically, the cytotoxicity of GNT has been attributed to estrogen receptor modulation, induction of apoptosis, inhibition of tyrosine kinases, and regulation of oxidative stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>]. In contrast, Apigenin has been reported to exert cytotoxicity through induction of cell cycle arrest, downregulation of anti-apoptotic proteins, and suppression of invasive and metastatic behavior via pathways such as PI3K/Akt and Wnt/&#946;-catenin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]. Our computational analyses support these mechanisms, highlighting PARP1 and ESR1 as central mediators of the observed cytotoxicity. In line with our computational predictions, the in vitro cytotoxicity assay in HCC1937 cells demonstrated inhibitory activity of both GNT and Apigenin, supporting the mechanistic trends predicted in silico. Although the absolute magnitude of the effects varied between computational and cellular models (as expected due to biological complexity and compound permeability), the direction of the effects&#8212;i.e., GNT preferentially modulating ESR1-associated signaling and Apigenin influencing DNA repair through PARP1&#8212;was consistent across analysis. This cross-validation suggests that the observed interactions are not isolated to a single methodological framework but reflect a coherent pharmacological pattern.</p><p id="Par78">It is also important to note that the IC<sub>50</sub> values obtained in this study are higher than those of conventional chemotherapeutics (e.g., doxorubicin or paclitaxel, which typically act at nanomolar concentrations) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>], suggesting that GNT and Apigenin may be more suitable as adjuvant or chemopreventive agents rather than stand-alone therapeutics. Nevertheless, their low predicted toxicity and multitarget regulatory potential make them attractive candidates for combination therapy, where they may enhance efficacy or reduce resistance when used alongside existing anticancer drugs.</p><sec id="Sec36"><title>Limitations and future direction</title><p id="Par79">Our work integrates systems pharmacology, molecular dynamics, energy-based binding assessment, and in vitro validation providing a comprehensive mechanistic model for the potential use of GNT and Apigenin in breast cancer treatment. Despite the promising results, this study has some limitations. The experimental validation was performed using a single TNBC cell line with a relatively small sample size, which may not fully capture the heterogeneity of breast cancer subtypes. The findings are based on an in vitro system that does not account for tumor microenvironment, metabolic stability, systemic bioavailability, or immune interactions. While both compounds demonstrated cytotoxicity at micromolar concentrations, their clinical translation may be limited by known challenges such as low solubility and rapid metabolism. Furthermore, this study did not include apo&#8211;protein MD simulations, which limits direct comparison of structural stabilization effects induced by ligand binding. The MD simulations were run as single trajectories without replicate runs using alternative random seeds. While the current 100 ns MD trajectories demonstrated stable ligand binding, longer simulations and replicate runs will be valuable to further confirm these stability trends. The observed cytotoxicity in HCC1937 cells supports the biological relevance of the compounds; however, it does not directly confirm ESR1 or PARP1 inhibition.</p><p id="Par80">Future work therefore includes in vivo validation in xenograft or orthotopic tumor models to confirm therapeutic efficacy and pharmacodynamic effects. Additionally, follow-up mechanistic studies are warranted to elucidate downstream signaling cascades modulated by PARP1 and ESR1 inhibition. Formulation-based approaches such as nanoparticle delivery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>], liposomal encapsulation, or prodrug derivatization could improve bioavailability and enhance tumor-specific uptake. Finally, extending the analysis to additional breast cancer subtypes&#8212;particularly ER-positive and HER2-enriched models&#8212;will be important to determine whether the therapeutic effects identified here are TNBC-specific or broadly generalizable.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec37"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par81">In conclusion, this study integrates network pharmacology, molecular docking, and cell-based assays to establish PARP1 and ESR1 as key targets of Apigenin and GNT in TNBC. The convergence of computational and in vitro findings supports their potential to modulate tumor-promoting pathways and induce cytotoxicity through estrogen receptor&#8211;independent mechanisms. From a translational standpoint, these findings suggest that GNT- and Apigenin-based derivatives, alone or in combination with existing therapeutic agents, may serve as low-toxicity adjuvants to improve treatment outcomes in breast cancer, particularly where endocrine resistance is present. Further optimization of compound bioavailability and validation in in vivo and multi-cell line models will be essential to determine their suitability for clinical deployment.</p></sec><sec id="Sec38" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="40360_2025_1082_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#8217;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Monica Arora: Concept, Methodology, Analysis, and Original-manuscript writing. Yahya S. Yaseen and Ammar A. Razzak Mahmood: Docking and Network Pharmacology analysis, Software. Sibghatullah Muhammad Ali Sangi, Sreeharsha Nagaraja: In vitro validation and review. Santosh Prasad Chaudhary Kurmi and Shankar Thapa: MD simulation, software, review and revision. All author agreed for publication.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the Deanship of Scientific Research, Vice Presidency for Graduate Studies and Scientific Research, King Faisal University, Saudi Arabia [Grant No. KFU254032].</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data will be made available on request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par82">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par83">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par84">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ADMET</term><def><p id="Par85">Absorption, Distribution, Metabolism, Excretion, and Toxicity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BP</term><def><p id="Par86">Biological Process</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CC</term><def><p id="Par87">Cellular Component</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DEG</term><def><p id="Par88">Differentially Expressed Gene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DMSO</term><def><p id="Par89">Dimethyl Sulfoxide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FEL</term><def><p id="Par90">Free Energy Landscape</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GO</term><def><p id="Par91">Gene Ontology</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HR</term><def><p id="Par92">Hazard Ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IC<sub>50</sub></term><def><p id="Par93">Half-Maximal Inhibitory Concentration</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KEGG</term><def><p id="Par94">Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MD</term><def><p id="Par95">Molecular Dynamics</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MM-GBSA</term><def><p id="Par96">Molecular Mechanics/Generalized Born Surface Area</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MTD</term><def><p id="Par97">Maximum Tolerated Dose</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MTT</term><def><p id="Par98">3-(4,5-Dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NP</term><def><p id="Par99">Network Pharmacology</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PARP1</term><def><p id="Par100">Poly (ADP-ribose) Polymerase 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCA</term><def><p id="Par101">Principal Component Analysis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PDB</term><def><p id="Par102">Protein Data Bank</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PI3K</term><def><p id="Par103">Phosphatidylinositol 3-Kinase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PPI</term><def><p id="Par104">Protein&#8211;Protein Interaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RMSD</term><def><p id="Par105">Root Mean Square Deviation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RMSF</term><def><p id="Par106">Root Mean Square Fluctuation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TCGA</term><def><p id="Par107">The Cancer Genome Atlas</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TNBC</term><def><p id="Par108">Triple-Negative Breast Cancer</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">WHO. Global cancer burden growing, amidst mounting need for services, WHO, 2024. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/pitcairnislands/news/detail-global/01-02-2024-global-cancer-burden-growing--amidst-mounting-need-for-services?utm_source=chatgpt.com">https://www.who.int/pitcairnislands/news/detail-global/01-02-2024-global-cancer-burden-growing--amidst-mounting-need-for-services?utm_source=chatgpt.com</ext-link> (accessed May 23, 2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11115397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38438207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasia</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maiti</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shivapooji</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Green synthesis of silver nano particles structural characterization and their antioxidant and anticancer potential using adenocarcinoma (A549) cell line</article-title><source>Indian J Pharm Educ Res</source><year>2024</year><volume>58</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>s995</fpage><lpage>1007</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5530/ijper.58.3s.99</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Sadik S, Vasia AK, Maiti BA, Shivapooji, Jana S. Green synthesis of silver nano particles structural characterization and their antioxidant and anticancer potential using adenocarcinoma (A549) cell line. Indian J Pharm Educ Res. 2024;58(3):s995&#8211;1007. 10.5530/ijper.58.3s.99.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural products in cancer therapy: Past, present and future</article-title><source>Nat Prod Bioprospect</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13659-020-00293-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33389713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7933288</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Huang M, Lu JJ, Ding J. Natural products in cancer therapy: Past, present and future. Nat Prod Bioprospect. 2021;11(1):5&#8211;13. 10.1007/s13659-020-00293-7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33389713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s13659-020-00293-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7933288</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alvizo-Rodr&#237;guez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrasco-Carballo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>L&#243;pez-V&#225;zquez</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hern&#225;ndez-Montes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hern&#225;ndez-Caballero</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome analysis of Triple-Negative HCC1937 and MDA-MB-231 breast cancer cells treated with Kalanchoe pinnata revealed the regulation of migration and invasion via the downregulation of the genes JAK2, ROCK1 and ROCK2</article-title><source>ACS Omega</source><year>2025</year><volume>10</volume><issue>28</issue><fpage>31187</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsomega.5c05895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40727786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12290928</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Alvizo-Rodr&#237;guez C, Carrasco-Carballo A, L&#243;pez-V&#225;zquez U, Hern&#225;ndez-Montes G, Hern&#225;ndez-Caballero ME. Transcriptome analysis of Triple-Negative HCC1937 and MDA-MB-231 breast cancer cells treated with Kalanchoe pinnata revealed the regulation of migration and invasion via the downregulation of the genes JAK2, ROCK1 and ROCK2. ACS Omega. 2025;10(28):31187&#8211;200. 10.1021/acsomega.5c05895.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40727786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/acsomega.5c05895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12290928</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almeida-Ferreira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of cold atmospheric plasma vs. Chemotherapy in Triple-Negative breast cancer: A systematic review</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2024</year><volume>25</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms25063254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10970295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38542225</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Almeida-Ferreira C, et al. Efficacy of cold atmospheric plasma vs. Chemotherapy in triple-negative breast cancer: a systematic review. Int J Mol Sci. 2024;25(6):1&#8211;28. 10.3390/ijms25063254.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms25063254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10970295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38542225</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farghadani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naidu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The anticancer mechanism of action of selected polyphenols in triple-negative breast cancer (TNBC)</article-title><source>Biomed Pharmacother</source><year>2023</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>115170</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2023.115170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37481930</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Farghadani R, Naidu R. The anticancer mechanism of action of selected polyphenols in triple-negative breast cancer (TNBC). Biomed Pharmacother. 2023;165:115170. 10.1016/j.biopha.2023.115170.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37481930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biopha.2023.115170</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sharifi-Rad J, et al. Genistein: an integrative overview of its mode of action, pharmacological properties, and health benefits. Oxid Med Cell Longev. 2021;2021:1&#8211;36. 10.1155/2021/3268136.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2021/3268136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8315847</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34336089</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of action of genistein on breast cancer and differential effects of different age stages</article-title><source>Pharm Biol</source><year>2025</year><volume>63</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13880209.2025.2469607</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39996512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11864014</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Xiang Z, Ma B, Pei X, Wang W, Gong W. Mechanism of action of genistein on breast cancer and differential effects of different age stages. Pharm Biol. 2025;63(1):141&#8211;55. 10.1080/13880209.2025.2469607.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39996512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/13880209.2025.2469607</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11864014</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sohel M, et al. Genistein, a potential phytochemical against breast cancer treatment-insight into the molecular mechanisms. Processes 2022;10(2):1&#8211;22. 10.3390/pr10020415.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ou M, et al. Mechanism of Apigenin against breast cancer stem cells: network pharmacology and experimental validation. Front. Pharmacol. 2024;5(November):1&#8211;18. 10.3389/fphar.2024.1496664.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fphar.2024.1496664</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11598448</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39605916</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lee HH, Jung J, Moon A, Kang H, Cho H. Antitumor and Anti-Invasive E Ff Ect of apigenin on human breast carcinoma through suppression of IL-6 expression, 2019. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms20133143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6651620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31252615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santell</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kieu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Helferich</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genistein inhibits growth of estrogen-independent human breast cancer cells in culture but not in athymic mice</article-title><source>J Nutr</source><year>2000</year><volume>130</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1665</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jn/130.7.1665</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10867033</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Santell RC, Kieu N, Helferich WG. Genistein inhibits growth of estrogen-independent human breast cancer cells in culture but not in athymic mice. J Nutr. 2000;130(7):1665&#8211;9. 10.1093/jn/130.7.1665.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10867033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jn/130.7.1665</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Opyrchal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeting PARP1: A promising approach for Next-Generation Poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase inhibitors</article-title><source>Curr Breast Cancer Rep</source><year>2025</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12609-025-00582-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12162764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40521389</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Ray A, Opyrchal M. Targeting PARP1: A promising approach for Next-Generation Poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase inhibitors. Curr Breast Cancer Rep. 2025;17(1):1&#8211;14. 10.1007/s12609-025-00582-5.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12609-025-00582-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12162764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40521389</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PARP-1 and its associated nucleases in DNA damage response</article-title><source>DNA Repair (Amst)</source><year>2019</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>102651</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dnarep.2019.102651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31302005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6764844</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Wang Y, Luo W, Wang Y. PARP-1 and its associated nucleases in DNA damage response. DNA Repair (Amst). 2019;81:102651. 10.1016/j.dnarep.2019.102651.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31302005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.dnarep.2019.102651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6764844</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>LC-MS profiling and cytotoxic activity of angiopteris Helferiana against HepG2 cell line: molecular insight to investigate anticancer agent</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2024</year><volume>19</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0309797</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11687663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39739862</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Pandey B, et al. LC-MS profiling and cytotoxic activity of angiopteris Helferiana against HepG2 cell line: molecular insight to investigate anticancer agent. PLoS ONE. 2024;19(12):1&#8211;24. 10.1371/journal.pone.0309797.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0309797</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11687663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39739862</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grinshpun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandusky</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fanning</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeselsohn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ESR1 activating mutations: from structure to clinical application</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta - Rev Cancer</source><year>2023</year><volume>1878</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>188830</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbcan.2022.188830</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36336145</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Grinshpun A, Chen V, Sandusky ZM, Fanning SW, Jeselsohn R. ESR1 activating mutations: from structure to clinical application. Biochim Biophys Acta - Rev Cancer. 2023;1878(1):188830. 10.1016/j.bbcan.2022.188830.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36336145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbcan.2022.188830</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rahmani AH, et al. The potential role of apigenin in cancer prevention and treatment. Molecules. Sep. 2022;27:6051. 10.3390/molecules27186051.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/molecules27186051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9505045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36144783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tuli HS, et al. Molecular mechanisms of action of genistein in cancer: recent advances. Front. Pharmacol. 2019;10(December):1&#8211;16. 10.3389/fphar.2019.01336.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fphar.2019.01336</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6910185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31866857</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pires DEV, Blundell TL, Ascher DB. PkCSM: predicting small-molecule pharmacokinetic and toxicity properties using graph-based signatures. J Med Chem. May 2015;58(9):4066&#8211;72. 10.1021/acs.jmedchem.5b00104.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/acs.jmedchem.5b00104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4434528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25860834</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Safran M et al. GeneCards Version 3: the human gene integrator., <italic toggle="yes">Database (Oxford).</italic>, vol. 2010, pp. 1&#8211;16, 2010. 10.1093/database/baq020<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/database/baq020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2938269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20689021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tribhuvan</surname><given-names>KU</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification, genomic localization, and functional validation of salt-stress-related LncRNAs in Indian mustard (Brassica juncea L)</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2024</year><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-024-10964-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39567864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11580500</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Tribhuvan KU, et al. Identification, genomic localization, and functional validation of salt-stress-related LncRNAs in Indian mustard (Brassica juncea L). BMC Genomics. 2024;25(1):1&#8211;12. 10.1186/s12864-024-10964-1.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39567864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12864-024-10964-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11580500</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Szklarczyk D, et al. Erratum: The STRING database in 2021: customizable protein&#8211;protein networks, and functional characterization of user-uploaded gene/measurement sets (Nucleic Acids Research (2021) 49 (D605&#8211;D612) 10.1093/nar/gkaa1074). Nucleic Acids Res. 2021;49(18):10800. 10.1093/nar/gkab835.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkaa1074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7779004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33237311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Otasek</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bou&#231;as</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pico</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Demchak</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytoscape automation: empowering workflow-based network analysis</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-019-1758-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31477170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6717989</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Otasek D, Morris JH, Bou&#231;as J, Pico AR, Demchak B. Cytoscape automation: empowering workflow-based network analysis. Genome Biol. 2019;20(1):1&#8211;15. 10.1186/s13059-019-1758-4.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31477170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13059-019-1758-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6717989</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>SX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ShinyGO: A graphical gene-set enrichment tool for animals and plants</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2020</year><volume>36</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2628</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btz931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31882993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7178415</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Ge SX, Jung D, Jung D, Yao R. ShinyGO: A graphical gene-set enrichment tool for animals and plants. Bioinformatics. 2020;36(8):2628&#8211;9. 10.1093/bioinformatics/btz931.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31882993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/bioinformatics/btz931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7178415</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thapa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manjunath</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LC-MS profiling and multi-target mechanistic insights of hibiscus rosa-sinensis in diabetes: network pharmacology, molecular docking, MD simulation, PCA, and in-vitro &#945; -amylase Inhibition</article-title><source>Pharmacol Res - Mod Chin Med</source><year>2025</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>100636</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.prmcm.2025.100636</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Thapa S, Nath S, Manjunath K. LC-MS profiling and multi-target mechanistic insights of hibiscus rosa-sinensis in diabetes: network pharmacology, molecular docking, MD simulation, PCA, and in-vitro &#945; -amylase Inhibition. Pharmacol Res - Mod Chin Med. 2025;16:100636. 10.1016/j.prmcm.2025.100636.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GEPIA2: an enhanced web server for large-scale expression profiling and interactive analysis</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>W556</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkz430</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31114875</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6602440</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Tang Z, Kang B, Li C, Chen T, Zhang Z. GEPIA2: an enhanced web server for large-scale expression profiling and interactive analysis. Nucleic Acids Res. 2019;47:W556&#8211;60. 10.1093/nar/gkz430.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31114875</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkz430</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6602440</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tang D, et al. SRplot: a free online platform for data visualization and graphing. PLoS One 2023;18(11 October):1&#8211;8. 10.1371/journal.pone.0294236.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0294236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10635526</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37943830</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Li T, et al. TIMER2.0 for analysis of tumor-infiltrating immune cells. Nucleic Acids Res. 2020;48(W1):W509&#8211;W514. 10.1093/NAR/GKAA407.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkaa407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7319575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32442275</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Li T, TIMER, et al. A web server for comprehensive analysis of Tumor-Infiltrating immune cells. Cancer Res. Nov. 2017;77(21):e108&#8211;10. 10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-17-0307.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-17-0307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6042652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29092952</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Velagapudi UK, et al. HHS public access. Design. 2020;5330&#8211;57. 10.1021/acs.jmedchem.8b01709.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosfield</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Stereospecific Lasofoxifene derivatives reveal the interplay between Estrogen receptor alpha stability and antagonistic activity in ESR1 mutant breast cancer cells</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2022</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.72512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9177151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35575456</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Hosfield DJ, et al. Stereospecific Lasofoxifene derivatives reveal the interplay between Estrogen receptor alpha stability and antagonistic activity in ESR1 mutant breast cancer cells. Elife. 2022;11:1&#8211;27. 10.7554/eLife.72512.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7554/eLife.72512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9177151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35575456</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thapa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nargund</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biradar</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karati</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In-silico investigation and drug likeliness studies of benzimidazole congeners: the new face of innovation</article-title><source>Inf Med Unlocked</source><year>2023</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>101213</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.imu.2023.101213</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Thapa S, Nargund SL, Biradar MS, Banerjee J, Karati D. In-silico investigation and drug likeliness studies of benzimidazole congeners: the new face of innovation. Inf Med Unlocked. 2023;38:101213. 10.1016/j.imu.2023.101213.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Thapa S, Nargund SL, Biradar MS. Molecular design and in-silico analysis of trisubstituted benzimidazole derivatives as Ftsz inhibitor. J Chem. 2023 Mar;2023(7):1&#8211;9. 10.1155/2023/9307613.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sriharsha</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Novel &#946;-L-1,3-thiazolidine pyrimidine nucleoside analogues: Design, synthesis, molecular docking, and anti-HIV activity</article-title><source>J Mol Struct</source><year>2023</year><volume>1294</volume><fpage>136304</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molstruc.2023.136304</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Sriharsha SN, et al. Novel &#946;-L-1,3-thiazolidine pyrimidine nucleoside analogues: Design, synthesis, molecular docking, and anti-HIV activity. J Mol Struct. 2023;1294:136304. 10.1016/j.molstruc.2023.136304.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">C P, et al. Repurposing terfenadine and domperidone for inhibition of apoptotic gene association in colorectal cancer: a systems pharmacology approach integrated with molecular docking, MD simulations, and post-MD simulation analysis. Bioinform Biol Insights. 2025;19:1-21. 10.1177/11779322251365019.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/11779322251365019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12374098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40861173</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thapa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Metri</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suresha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular docking, drug &#8211; likeness properties, and toxicity prediction of alkaloidal phytoconstituents of Piper longum against monoamine oxidase enzyme &#8211; A as an anti &#8211; depressive agent</article-title><source>Discov Chem</source><year>2025</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s44371-025-00188-x</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Prasad S, Thapa S, Metri SM, Suresha M. Molecular docking, drug &#8211; likeness properties, and toxicity prediction of alkaloidal phytoconstituents of Piper longum against monoamine oxidase enzyme &#8211; A as an anti &#8211; depressive agent. Discov Chem. 2025;2:1&#8211;18. 10.1007/s44371-025-00188-x.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kurmi SPC, Thapa S, Karati D. Molecular docking and pharmacokinetic evaluations of curcumin-based scaffolds as MDM2&#8211;p53 inhibitors. Discov Chem. 2025;2(1):53. 10.1007/s44371-025-00128-9.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kiran S, et al. Integrated computational approach revealed the potential inhibitory effect of xanthone derivatives against Marburg virus nucleocapsid. VirusDisease. 2025;36(3):415&#8211;427. 10.1007/s13337-025-00933-x.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s13337-025-00933-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12635017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">41281989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyambo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular docking, molecular dynamics simulations and binding free energy studies of interactions between Mycobacterium tuberculosis Pks13, PknG and bioactive constituents of extremophilic bacteria</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-024-57124-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38514663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10957976</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Nyambo K, et al. Molecular docking, molecular dynamics simulations and binding free energy studies of interactions between Mycobacterium tuberculosis Pks13, PknG and bioactive constituents of extremophilic bacteria. Sci Rep. 2024;14(1):1&#8211;22. 10.1038/s41598-024-57124-9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38514663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-024-57124-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10957976</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increased sensitivity of BRCA defective triple negative breast tumors to Plumbagin through induction of DNA double strand breaks (DSB)</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>26631</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep26631</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27220670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4879579</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Nair RS, et al. Increased sensitivity of BRCA defective triple negative breast tumors to Plumbagin through induction of DNA double strand breaks (DSB). Sci Rep. 2016;6:26631. 10.1038/srep26631.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27220670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/srep26631</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4879579</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abu-Marzoq</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>E-MQA-BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aliwaini</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The anticancer effects A new benzimidazole on HCC1937 breast cancer cell line</article-title><source>Onkol I Radioter</source><year>2024</year><volume>18</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Abu-Marzoq LF, Ali E-MQA-BM, Aliwaini SH. The anticancer effects A new benzimidazole on HCC1937 breast cancer cell line. Onkol I Radioter. 2024;18(2):1&#8211;8.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genistein inhibits proliferation of BRCA1 mutated breast cancer cells: the GPR30-Akt axis as a potential target</article-title><source>J Cancer Prev</source><year>2019</year><volume>24</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15430/jcp.2019.24.4.197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31950019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6951321</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Kim GY, et al. Genistein inhibits proliferation of BRCA1 mutated breast cancer cells: the GPR30-Akt axis as a potential target. J Cancer Prev. 2019;24(4):197&#8211;207. 10.15430/jcp.2019.24.4.197.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31950019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.15430/JCP.2019.24.4.197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6951321</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Targeting breast cancer stem cells in triple-negative breast cancer using a combination of LBH589 and salinomycin</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source><year>2015</year><volume>151</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10549-015-3376-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25904215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4587767</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Kai M, et al. Targeting breast cancer stem cells in triple-negative breast cancer using a combination of LBH589 and salinomycin. Breast Cancer Res Treat. 2015;151(2):281&#8211;94. 10.1007/s10549-015-3376-5.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25904215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10549-015-3376-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4587767</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zha</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and in vitro anticancer evaluation of novel flavonoid-based amide derivatives as regulators of the PI3K/AKT signal pathway for TNBC treatment</article-title><source>RSC Med Chem</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1082</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/d2md00148a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36324491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9491353</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Zha D, et al. Synthesis and in vitro anticancer evaluation of novel flavonoid-based amide derivatives as regulators of the PI3K/AKT signal pathway for TNBC treatment. RSC Med Chem. 2022;13(9):1082&#8211;99. 10.1039/d2md00148a.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36324491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1039/d2md00148a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9491353</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Network pharmacology: a bright guiding light on the way to explore the personalized precise medication of traditional Chinese medicine</article-title><source>Chin Med (United Kingdom)</source><year>2023</year><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13020-023-00853-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10631104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37941061</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Li L, et al. Network pharmacology: a bright guiding light on the way to explore the personalized precise medication of traditional Chinese medicine. Chin Med (United Kingdom). 2023;18(1):1&#8211;19. 10.1186/s13020-023-00853-2.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13020-023-00853-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10631104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37941061</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arif</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bukhari</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mustafa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albeshr</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Network Pharmacology and experimental validation to explore the potential mechanism of Nigella sativa for the treatment of breast cancer</article-title><source>Pharmaceuticals</source><year>2024</year><volume>17</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ph17050617</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11124279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38794187</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Arif R, Bukhari SA, Mustafa G, Ahmed S, Albeshr MF. Network Pharmacology and experimental validation to explore the potential mechanism of Nigella sativa for the treatment of breast cancer. Pharmaceuticals. 2024;17(5):1&#8211;23. 10.3390/ph17050617.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ph17050617</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11124279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38794187</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">N B. Network pharmacology-based investigation on the mechanism of tetrandrine against breast cancer. Phytomedicine Plus. 2023;3(1):100381. 10.1016/j.phyplu.2022.100381.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scherbakov</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andreeva</surname><given-names>OE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apigenin inhibits growth of breast cancer cells: the role of era and HER2/neu</article-title><source>Acta Naturae</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32607/20758251-2015-7-3-133-139</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26483970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4610175</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Scherbakov AM, Andreeva OE. Apigenin inhibits growth of breast cancer cells: the role of era and HER2/neu. Acta Naturae. 2015;7(3):133&#8211;9. 10.32607/20758251-2015-7-3-133-139.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26483970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4610175</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR49" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bigsby</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nephew</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apigenin inhibits antiestrogen-resistant breast cancer cell growth through Estrogen receptor-&#945;-dependent and Estrogen receptor-&#945;-independent mechanisms</article-title><source>Mol Cancer Ther</source><year>2008</year><volume>7</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>2096</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1535-7163.MCT-07-2350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18645020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2559959</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49" publication-type="journal">Long X, Fan M, Bigsby RM, Nephew KP. Apigenin inhibits antiestrogen-resistant breast cancer cell growth through Estrogen receptor-&#945;-dependent and Estrogen receptor-&#945;-independent mechanisms. Mol Cancer Ther. 2008;7(7):2096&#8211;108. 10.1158/1535-7163.MCT-07-2350.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18645020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1535-7163.MCT-07-2350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2559959</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ji X, et al. A mini-review of flavone isomers apigenin and genistein in prostate cancer treatment. Front Pharmacol. 2022;13:1&#8211;9. 10.3389/fphar.2022.851589.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fphar.2022.851589</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8962830</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35359832</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahbub</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Maitre</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jordan-Mahy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of apigenin and chemotherapy combination treatments on apoptosis-related genes and proteins in acute leukaemia cell lines</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-11441-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35614109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9132959</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Mahbub AA, Le Maitre CL, Cross NA, Jordan-Mahy N. The effect of apigenin and chemotherapy combination treatments on apoptosis-related genes and proteins in acute leukaemia cell lines. Sci Rep. 2022;12(1):1&#8211;17. 10.1038/s41598-022-11441-z.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35614109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-022-11441-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9132959</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR52" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genistein-triggered anticancer activity against liver cancer cell line HepG2 involves ROS generation, mitochondrial apoptosis, G2/M cell cycle arrest and Inhibition of cell migrationand Inhibition of cell migration</article-title><source>Arch Med Sci</source><year>2019</year><volume>15</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1001</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5114/aoms.2018.78742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31360194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6657265</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR52" publication-type="journal">Zhang Q, Bao J, Yang J. Genistein-triggered anticancer activity against liver cancer cell line HepG2 involves ROS generation, mitochondrial apoptosis, G2/M cell cycle arrest and Inhibition of cell migrationand Inhibition of cell migration. Arch Med Sci. 2019;15(4):1001&#8211;9. 10.5114/aoms.2018.78742.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31360194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5114/aoms.2018.78742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6657265</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR53" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rath</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute exposure of apigenin induces hepatotoxicity in Swiss mice</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0031964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3281105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22359648</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR53" publication-type="journal">Singh P, Mishra SK, Noel S, Sharma S, Rath SK. Acute exposure of apigenin induces hepatotoxicity in Swiss mice. PLoS ONE. 2012;7(2):1&#8211;11. 10.1371/journal.pone.0031964.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0031964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3281105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22359648</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR54" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Divya Rajaselvi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jida</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sujith</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beegum</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nisha</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxicity prediction and analysis of flavonoid apigenin as a histone deacetylase inhibitor: an in-silico approach</article-title><source>Silico Pharmacol</source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40203-023-00170-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10630278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37941890</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR54" publication-type="journal">Divya Rajaselvi N, Jida MD, Nair DB, Sujith S, Beegum N, Nisha AR. Toxicity prediction and analysis of flavonoid apigenin as a histone deacetylase inhibitor: an in-silico approach. Silico Pharmacol. 2023;11(1):1&#8211;12. 10.1007/s40203-023-00170-4.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40203-023-00170-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10630278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37941890</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wang M, Firrman J, Liu LS, Yam K. A review on flavonoid apigenin: dietary intake, ADME, antimicrobial effects, and interactions with human gut microbiota. Biomed Res Int. 2019;2019:1&#8211;18. 10.1155/2019/7010467.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2019/7010467</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6817918</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31737673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR56" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanev</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atemin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoynov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aleksandrov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PARP1 roles in DNA repair and DNA replication: the basi(c)s of PARP inhibitor efficacy and resistance</article-title><source>Semin Oncol</source><year>2024</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.seminoncol.2023.08.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37714792</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR56" publication-type="journal">Kanev PB, Atemin A, Stoynov S, Aleksandrov R. PARP1 roles in DNA repair and DNA replication: the basi(c)s of PARP inhibitor efficacy and resistance. Semin Oncol. 2024;51:1&#8211;2. 10.1053/j.seminoncol.2023.08.001.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37714792</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.seminoncol.2023.08.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR57" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchard</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rouleau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poirier</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PARP-1, a determinant of cell survival in response to DNA damage</article-title><source>Exp Hematol</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>446</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0301-472X(03)00083-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12829019</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR57" publication-type="journal">Bouchard VJ, Rouleau M, Poirier GG. PARP-1, a determinant of cell survival in response to DNA damage. Exp Hematol. 2003;31:446&#8211;54. 10.1016/S0301-472X(03)00083-3.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12829019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0301-472x(03)00083-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR58" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oturkar</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ESR1 and p53 interactome alteration defines mechanisms of Tamoxifen response in luminal breast cancer</article-title><source>iScience</source><year>2024</year><volume>27</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>109995</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.isci.2024.109995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38868185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11166704</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR58" publication-type="journal">Oturkar CC, et al. ESR1 and p53 interactome alteration defines mechanisms of Tamoxifen response in luminal breast cancer. iScience. 2024;27(6):109995. 10.1016/j.isci.2024.109995.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38868185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.isci.2024.109995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11166704</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR59" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spring</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bardia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wander</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ESR1 mutation as an emerging clinical biomarker in metastatic hormone receptor-positive breast cancer</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13058-021-01462-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34392831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8365900</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR59" publication-type="journal">Brett JO, Spring LM, Bardia A, Wander SA. ESR1 mutation as an emerging clinical biomarker in metastatic hormone receptor-positive breast cancer. Breast Cancer Res. 2021;23(1):1&#8211;15. 10.1186/s13058-021-01462-3.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34392831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13058-021-01462-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8365900</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR60" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genistein as a potential anticancer agent against ovarian cancer</article-title><source>J Tradit Complement Med</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2225-4110(16)30082-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24716121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3942921</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR60" publication-type="journal">Lee JY, Kim H, Song YS. Genistein as a potential anticancer agent against ovarian cancer. J Tradit Complement Med. 2012;2(2):96&#8211;104. 10.1016/S2225-4110(16)30082-7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24716121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s2225-4110(16)30082-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3942921</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kumi-Diaka J, Sanderson NA, Hall A. The mediating role of caspase-3 protease in the intracellular mechanism of genistein-induced apoptosis in human prostatic carcinoma cell lines DU145 and LNCaP. Biol Cell. 2000;92(8&#8211;9):595&#8211;604. 10.1016/S0248-4900(00)01109-6.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0248-4900(00)01109-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11374438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR62" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Javed</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Apigenin role as cell-signaling pathways modulator: implications in cancer prevention and treatment</article-title><source>Cancer Cell Int</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12935-021-01888-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33794890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8017783</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR62" publication-type="journal">Javed Z, et al. Apigenin role as cell-signaling pathways modulator: implications in cancer prevention and treatment. Cancer Cell Int. 2021;21(1):1&#8211;11. 10.1186/s12935-021-01888-x.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33794890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12935-021-01888-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8017783</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR63" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naponelli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocchetti</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mangieri</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apigenin: molecular mechanisms and therapeutic potential against cancer spreading</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2024</year><volume>25</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms25105569</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11122459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38791608</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR63" publication-type="journal">Naponelli V, Rocchetti MT, Mangieri D. Apigenin: molecular mechanisms and therapeutic potential against cancer spreading. Int J Mol Sci. 2024;25(10):1&#8211;33. 10.3390/ijms25105569.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms25105569</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11122459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38791608</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lord CJ, Ashworth A. PARP inhibitors: synthetic lethality in the clinic. Science. 2017;355(6330):1152&#8211;1158. 10.1126/science.aam7344.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.aam7344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6175050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28302823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR65" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Network pharmacology: the next paradigm in drug discovery</article-title><source>Nat Chem Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>4</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>682</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchembio.118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18936753</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR65" publication-type="journal">Hopkins AL. Network pharmacology: the next paradigm in drug discovery. Nat Chem Biol. 2008;4(11):682&#8211;90. 10.1038/nchembio.118.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18936753</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nchembio.118</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR66" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sulforaphane, a dietary component of broccoli/broccoli sprouts, inhibits breast cancer stem cells</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>16</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2580</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-09-2937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20388854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2862133</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR66" publication-type="journal">Li Y, et al. Sulforaphane, a dietary component of broccoli/broccoli sprouts, inhibits breast cancer stem cells. Clin Cancer Res. 2010;16(9):2580&#8211;90. 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-09-2937.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20388854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-09-2937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2862133</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR67" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walle</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methylation of dietary flavones increases their metabolic stability and chemopreventive effects</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>5002</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms10115002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20087474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2808020</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR67" publication-type="journal">Walle T. Methylation of dietary flavones increases their metabolic stability and chemopreventive effects. Int J Mol Sci. 2009;10(11):5002&#8211;19. 10.3390/ijms10115002.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20087474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms10115002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2808020</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR68" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apigenin inhibits the proliferation and invasion of osteosarcoma cells by suppressing the Wnt/&#946;-catenin signaling pathway</article-title><source>Oncol Rep</source><year>2015</year><volume>34</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1035</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/or.2015.4022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26035210</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR68" publication-type="journal">Liu X, Li L, Lv L, Chen D, Shen L, Xie Z. Apigenin inhibits the proliferation and invasion of osteosarcoma cells by suppressing the Wnt/&#946;-catenin signaling pathway. Oncol Rep. 2015;34(2):1035&#8211;41. 10.3892/or.2015.4022.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26035210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3892/or.2015.4022</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR69" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of genistein and synergistic action in combination with eicosapentaenoic acid on the growth of breast cancer cell lines</article-title><source>J Cancer Res Clin Oncol</source><year>2000</year><volume>126</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>448</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004320050012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10961387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12165226</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR69" publication-type="journal">Nakagawa H, et al. Effects of genistein and synergistic action in combination with eicosapentaenoic acid on the growth of breast cancer cell lines. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol. 2000;126(8):448&#8211;54. 10.1007/s004320050012.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10961387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/PL00021280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12165226</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR70" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naeem</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anticancer perspectives of genistein: a comprehensive review</article-title><source>Int J Food Prop</source><year>2023</year><volume>26</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>3305</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10942912.2023.2281257</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR70" publication-type="journal">Naeem H, et al. Anticancer perspectives of genistein: a comprehensive review. Int J Food Prop. 2023;26(2):3305&#8211;41. 10.1080/10942912.2023.2281257.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR71" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oxidative stress triggered by apigenin induces apoptosis in a comprehensive panel of human cervical Cancer-Derived cell lines</article-title><source>Oxid Med Cell Longev</source><year>2017</year><volume>2017</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2017/1512745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5278229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28191273</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR71" publication-type="journal">Souza R P, et al. Oxidative stress triggered by apigenin induces apoptosis in a comprehensive panel of human cervical Cancer-Derived cell lines. Oxid Med Cell Longev. 2017;2017:1&#8211;18. 10.1155/2017/1512745.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2017/1512745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5278229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28191273</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR72" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choudhury</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ganguli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dastidar</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Das</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chakrabarti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apigenin shows synergistic anticancer activity with Curcumin by binding at different sites of tubulin</article-title><source>Biochimie</source><year>2013</year><volume>95</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1297</fpage><lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biochi.2013.02.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23485682</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR72" publication-type="journal">Choudhury D, Ganguli A, Dastidar DG, Acharya BR, Das A, Chakrabarti G. Apigenin shows synergistic anticancer activity with Curcumin by binding at different sites of tubulin. Biochimie. 2013;95(6):1297&#8211;309. 10.1016/j.biochi.2013.02.010.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23485682</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biochi.2013.02.010</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kaewmanee M, Limpaiboon T, Ngernyuang N. Apigenin induces apoptosis and inhibits migration in human cholangiocarcinoma cells. Toxics. 2025;13(2):1&#8211;11. 10.3390/toxics13020112.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/toxics13020112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11860412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39997927</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR74" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rend&#243;n</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the effects of genistein in vitro as a chemopreventive agent for colorectal Cancer&#8212;Strategy to improve its efficiency when administered orally</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2022</year><volume>27</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules27207042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9612062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36296636</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR74" publication-type="journal">Rend&#243;n JP, et al. Evaluation of the effects of genistein in vitro as a chemopreventive agent for colorectal Cancer&#8212;Strategy to improve its efficiency when administered orally. Molecules. 2022;27(20):1&#8211;20. 10.3390/molecules27207042.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/molecules27207042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9612062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36296636</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR75" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Konstantinou</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gioxari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dimitriou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panoutsopoulos</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panagiotopoulos</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular pathways of genistein activity in breast cancer cells</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2024</year><volume>25</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms25105556</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11122029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38791595</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR75" publication-type="journal">Konstantinou EK, Gioxari A, Dimitriou M, Panoutsopoulos GI, Panagiotopoulos AA. Molecular pathways of genistein activity in breast cancer cells. Int J Mol Sci. 2024;25(10):1&#8211;22. 10.3390/ijms25105556.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms25105556</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11122029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38791595</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR76" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anticancer effects and molecular mechanisms of apigenin in cervical cancer cells</article-title><source>Cancers (Basel)</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cancers14071824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8998024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35406599</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR76" publication-type="journal">Chen YH, Wu JX, Yang SF, Yang CK, Chen TH, Hsiao YH. Anticancer effects and molecular mechanisms of apigenin in cervical cancer cells. Cancers (Basel). 2022;14(7):1&#8211;20. 10.3390/cancers14071824.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/cancers14071824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8998024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35406599</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR77" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fossatelli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maroccia</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiorentini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonucci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resources for human health from the plant kingdom: the potential role of the flavonoid apigenin in cancer counteraction</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2024</year><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms25010251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10778966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38203418</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR77" publication-type="journal">Fossatelli L, Maroccia Z, Fiorentini C, Bonucci M. Resources for human health from the plant kingdom: the potential role of the flavonoid apigenin in cancer counteraction. Int J Mol Sci. 2024;25(1):1&#8211;18. 10.3390/ijms25010251.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms25010251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10778966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38203418</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR78" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apigenin in cancer therapy: Anti-cancer effects and mechanisms of action</article-title><source>Cell Biosci</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13578-017-0179-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29034071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5629766</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR78" publication-type="journal">Yan X, Qi M, Li P, Zhan Y, Shao H. Apigenin in cancer therapy: Anti-cancer effects and mechanisms of action. Cell Biosci. 2017;7(1):1&#8211;16. 10.1186/s13578-017-0179-x.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29034071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13578-017-0179-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5629766</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tassone P, et al. BRCA1 expression modulates chemosensitivity of BRCA1-defective HCC1937 human breast cancer cells. Br J Cancer. 2003;88(8):1285&#8211;1291. 10.1038/sj.bjc.6600859.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.bjc.6600859</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2747554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12698198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR80" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alnaim</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and characterization of silver nano particles of Kaempferol and their application as antibacterial and against prostate cells (Pc-3)</article-title><source>Front Heal Inf</source><year>2024</year><volume>13</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>66</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR80" publication-type="journal">Alnaim AA, et al. Synthesis and characterization of silver nano particles of Kaempferol and their application as antibacterial and against prostate cells (Pc-3). Front Heal Inf. 2024;13(4):155&#8211;66.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>