<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="brief-report" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Breast Cancer</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Breast Cancer</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1573</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jbrcan</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JBC</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Breast Cancer</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1738-6756</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2092-9900</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Korean Breast Cancer Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12768587</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12768587.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12768587</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12768587</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41311334</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4048/jbc.2025.0121</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Study Protocol</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Prospective Multicenter Study Comparing Magnetic Resonance Imaging and Ultrasonography for Second Breast Cancer Surveillance in Women With Prior Breast Cancer and Dense Breasts: KBCSG-27 Trial</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9704-8112</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names initials="YW">Yun-Woo</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7332-3853</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names initials="YM">Young Mi</given-names></name><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0865-2236</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="K">Kyunga</given-names></name><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5102-0536</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="MJ">Min-Ji</given-names></name><xref rid="A3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9228-022X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="MK">Myoung Kyoung</given-names></name><xref rid="A4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9546-100X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names initials="J">Jonghan</given-names></name><xref rid="A5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0399-7956</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names initials="ES">Eun Sook</given-names></name><xref rid="A4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Radiology, Soonchunhyang University Seoul Hospital, Seoul, <country>Korea</country>.</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Radiology, Inje University Busan Paik Hospital, Busan, <country>Korea</country>.</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Biomedical Statistics Center, Research Institute for Future Medicine, Samsung Medical Center, Seoul, <country>Korea</country>.</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Radiology, Samsung Medical Center, Sungkyunkwan University School of Medicine, Seoul, <country>Korea</country>.</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Division of Breast Surgery, Department of Surgery, Samsung Medical Center, Sungkyunkwan University School of Medicine, Seoul, <country>Korea</country>.</aff><author-notes><corresp>Correspondence to Eun Sook Ko. Department of Radiology, Samsung Medical Center, Sungkyunkwan University School of Medicine, 81 Irwon-ro, Gangnam-gu, Seoul 06351, Korea. <email>mathilda0330@gmail.com</email></corresp><corresp>Correspondence to Jonghan Yu. Division of Breast Surgery, Department of Surgery, Samsung Medical Center, Sungkyunkwan University School of Medicine, 81 Irwon-ro, Gangnam-gu, Seoul 06351, Korea. <email>jonghan.yu@samsung.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>28</volume><issue>6</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">504063</issue-id><fpage>427</fpage><lpage>436</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>14</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>04</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>06</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-01-06 16:25:13.910"><day>06</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Authors 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Korean Breast Cancer Society</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jbc-28-427.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>Surveillance guidelines following breast cancer surgery recommend mammography as the sole imaging modality. However, the accuracy of mammography is low in younger women and in those with dense breast tissue. Additional imaging modalities, such as ultrasonography and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), may offer diagnostic benefits. This prospective, multicenter study (KBCSG-27) aims to compare the diagnostic performances of mammography, ultrasonography, and MRI for detecting second breast cancer (SBC) in women with a personal history of breast cancer (PHBC) and dense breasts.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>This study will recruit approximately 1,756 women, aged 20&#8211;75 years, who were treated for stage 0&#8211;III breast cancer and have dense breast tissue on mammography. Participants will undergo two annual breast screenings, each consisting of mammography, ultrasonography, and MRI. MRI will be performed using either abbreviated magnetic resonance imaging (AB-MRI) or full-protocol magnetic resonance imaging (FP-MRI), which will be randomly assigned such that each participant receives both protocols alternately. Radiologists will independently interpret all images. A combination of pathology results and 12-month follow-up will serve as the reference standard. A patient-reported outcome (PRO) tool will be used to assess patients&#8217; experiences and preferences between AB-MRI and FP-MRI. The primary objective is to compare the cancer detection rates of ultrasonography versus AB-MRI and ultrasonography versus FP-MRI. Secondary outcomes include comparisons of the invasive cancer detection rates, abnormal interpretation rates, sensitivity, specificity, positive and negative predictive values, accuracy, and interval cancer rates. Subgroup analyses will be conducted based on age, menopausal status, mammographic breast density, and molecular subtype. Additionally, PRO results of AB-MRI and FP-MRI will be compared.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>This ongoing, prospective, multicenter study aims to evaluate the performance of ultrasonography, AB-MRI, and FP-MRI in SBC surveillance in women with PHBC and dense breasts. Enrollment is expected to be completed by 2025, with results anticipated after 2028.</p></sec><sec><title>Trial Registration</title><p>ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT05797545" ext-link-type="uri">NCT05797545</ext-link>. Registered on April 23, 2023</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Breast Neoplasms</kwd><kwd>Clinical Trial</kwd><kwd>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</kwd><kwd>Mass Screening</kwd><kwd>Ultrasonography</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source country="KR"><institution-wrap><institution>Korean Society of Breast Imaging and Korean Society for Breast Screening</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>KSBI &amp; KSFBS-2023-01</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source country="KR"><institution-wrap><institution>Korean Breast Cancer Study Group</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>KBCSG-27</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source country="KR"><institution-wrap><institution>Bayer Korea</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="CrossRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/100018090</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="other1"><title>INTRODUCION</title><p>Women with a personal history of breast cancer (PHBC) remain at significant risk of developing a second breast cancer (SBC) in the ipsilateral or contralateral breast after treatment, which is often associated with systemic metastasis and poor prognosis [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Early detection of SBC is crucial for improving survival and quality of life [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Currently, guidelines recommend annual mammography as the only imaging modality for postoperative surveillance, in addition to clinical assessment [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>Mammography is the only method proven to reduce breast cancer-related mortality in randomized controlled trials. However, the accuracy of mammography is low in younger women and in those with dense breasts [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Asian women, including those from Korea, have a higher proportion of dense breasts than that of women of other racial groups [<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Additionally, a large cohort study reported that approximately 15% of women may develop interval cancer within five years after surgery despite normal mammography results [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Therefore, mammography for the follow-up of women with dense breasts may not be sufficient, potentially limiting early diagnosis and treatment. Thus, supplemental imaging modalities are necessary.</p><p>Breast ultrasonography and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) can be considered supplemental imaging modalities. Adding breast ultrasonography to mammography in normal screening populations results in the detection of an average of 4.2 additional breast cancers per 1,000 ultrasonography examinations [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref><xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Breast ultrasonography has many advantages, including easy accessibility and financial benefits provided by the National Health Insurance Service&#8217;s special treatment provisions in Korea, which limit out-of-pocket medical expenses to 5% for up to five years post-cancer diagnosis. Despite its advantages, breast ultrasonography also has notable disadvantages, including significant operator dependency and the labor-intensive nature of the procedure, which takes approximately 20&#8211;30 minutes per examination. Additionally, both ultrasonography and MRI are associated with high false-positive rates, often leading to unnecessary follow-up tests and biopsies, which may increase healthcare costs [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. MRI has been primarily used to screen high-risk groups, such as patients with hereditary breast cancer [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. However, several single-center and multicenter prospective studies have confirmed that MRI screening has high sensitivity [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref><xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In 2018, the American College of Radiology included women younger than 50 years who had undergone breast-conserving surgery for breast cancer in the supplemental MRI screening group, as the risk of developing SBC was greater than 20% [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Although women with PHBC are at high risk of developing SBC, the level of risk varies widely. Most women with PHBC have an intermediate risk level (&gt; 15% but &lt; 20%) for developing new breast cancer [<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Therefore, because most women with PHBC do not belong to high-risk groups, full-protocol MRI (FP-MRI) is neither cost-effective nor efficient.</p><p>The relatively recently introduced abbreviated MRI (AB-MRI) is a method designed to enhance accessibility by using selected time sequences from FP-MRI, thereby reducing examination time and costs [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The composition of the sequences can be adjusted in various ways, and image acquisition is typically completed within 10 minutes. AB-MRI has demonstrated a diagnostic accuracy equivalent to that of FP-MRI for breast cancer screening [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref><xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref><xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Additionally, AB-MRI has acceptable diagnostic performance in women with PHBC, which is comparable to that of FP-MRI [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. However, most existing studies are retrospective in nature, and no prior research has investigated patient preference for AB-MRI over FP-MRI using patient-reported outcome (PRO) measurements. Therefore, this report aims to describe the protocol for a prospective, multicenter, comparative study of mammography, ultrasonography, and MRI, specifically focusing on women with dense breasts and PHBC.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>METHODS</title><p>This study was funded by the Korean Breast Cancer Study Group (KBCSG-27), Korean Society of Breast Imaging, Korean Society for Breast Screening (KSBI &amp; KSFBS-2023-01), and Bayer Korea. The study protocol was approved by the Institutional Review Boards (IRBs) of the three participating centers: Samsung Medical Center (2022-11-076), Soonchunhyang University Seoul Hospital (2023-03-010), and Inje University Paik Hospital (2023-06-032). Written informed consent will be obtained from all enrolled participants to allow their data to be used. Protocol version 1.1.5, finalized on May 14, 2025, was based on the version initially submitted for IRB review in November 2022.</p><sec><title>Study design</title><p>This is a prospective, multicenter, intraindividual, comparative clinical trial. Participants will be recruited from three tertiary academic centers&#8212;Samsung Medical Center, Soonchunhyang University Seoul Hospital, and Inje University Paik Hospital&#8212;which will provide multimodal postoperative surveillance with high-quality standards.</p><p>Each participant will be assigned a unique identification number at the time of enrollment according to the institution and registration order. All eligible participants will be randomly assigned to one of two MRI protocol sequences for the first and second round screenings: either AB-MRI followed by FP-MRI or FP-MRI followed by AB-MRI. In the first round of screening (baseline), the assigned MRI (either AB-MRI or FP-MRI) will be performed on the same day as the mammography and ultrasonography. The second round of screening will be conducted at least one year later and will include mammography, ultrasonography, and an alternate MRI protocol not used in the first round. A PRO measurement designed to assess patient discomfort and preference will be administered via an individual link and sent to the participants for their responses after the imaging tests. The reference standard will include pathology results, imaging findings, or clinical follow-up outcomes obtained from medical records at least 1 year after the second round of screening. A flowchart of the study design is shown in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. Data will be collected using an electronic case report form (eCRF) (<xref rid="S1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Data 1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Study flowchart.</title><p>DCE = dynamic contrast-enhanced; MRI = magnetic resonance imaging; AB-MRI = abbreviated magnetic resonance imaging; PRO = patient-reported outcome; FP-MRI = full-protocol magnetic resonance imaging.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jbc-28-427-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Randomization and allocation</title><p>Randomization was performed by an independent statistician who was not involved in patient enrollment or assessment. A computer-generated permuted block design was used to allocate participants to one of the two MRI protocol groups: AB-MRI followed by FP-MRI or FP-MRI followed by AB-MRI. Participants were randomized in a 1:1 ratio between the two MRI protocol groups. A randomization list was generated centrally and applied sequentially at each site. Each participant was assigned a unique randomization number (R-[1-digit institution number]-[4-digit serial number]) upon registration. The study investigators had access to the randomization sequence and enrolled participants in a predetermined order. Because the imaging protocol was fixed upon assignment and conducted only once per round, no interim modification or reallocation was allowed.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical consideration</title><p>This protocol was registered in the International Trial Registry (ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:clinical-trial" xlink:href="NCT05797545">NCT05797545</ext-link>) on April 23, 2023. Written informed consent will be obtained from all participants. The first participant was enrolled in August 2023. At the time of report submission (May 2025), patient enrollment is ongoing at two centers (Soonchunhyang University Seoul Hospital and Inje University Paik Hospital). Enrollment completion is expected in 2025, and the study results will be presented in 2028. Given the observational nature of the study, no formal data monitoring committee has been established. Regular internal audits are conducted to ensure protocol adherence. All protocol amendments will be submitted to the IRBs of the participating centers and updated at ClinicalTrials.gov. The investigators report no financial or competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Study population</title><p>Women aged 20&#8211;75 years who underwent breast cancer surgery for ductal carcinoma in situ or invasive breast cancer (stages 0&#8211;3), and who are classified as having mammographic breast density pattern C (heterogeneously dense) or D (extremely dense) according to the Breast Imaging Reporting and Data System (BI-RADS) [<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], based on their most recent mammogram assessed using the artificial intelligence-based assessment tool (Lunit INSIGHT for Mammography; Lunit Inc., Seoul, Korea), are eligible for inclusion. Women who have not undergone any breast imaging examinations within the past six months will be included in this study.</p><p>The exclusion criteria are as follows: women with symptoms or signs of breast cancer recurrence; women diagnosed with regional recurrence (including axillary lymph nodes, supraclavicular and infraclavicular lymph nodes, and internal mammary lymph nodes) or distant metastasis; women who have undergone bilateral mastectomy; women undergoing chemotherapy for malignancies in another organ; women who are pregnant or breastfeeding; women with a glomerular filtration rate &lt; 30 mL/min/1.73 m<sup>2</sup> or with end-stage renal disease who are currently on dialysis; women with severe claustrophobia; women with magnetic resonance-unsafe metallic implants (including tissue expanders); and women with a history of severe contrast agent reactions (including anaphylactic reactions and shortness of breath).</p></sec><sec><title>Image acquisition</title><p>Mammography is performed using a digital mammography unit with craniocaudal and mediolateral oblique views. Attending breast radiologists perform hand-held whole-breast ultrasonography using a high-resolution linear probe (&#8805; 10 MHz), blinded to concurrent mammography or MRI findings.</p><p>Breast MRI is performed in the prone position using 1.5 T or higher MRI scanners with a dedicated breast coil. For AB-MRI, various MRI scanners and protocols can be used across the three participating institutions; however, the imaging procedure must be completed within 10 minutes. The required protocol includes both T2-weighted and contrast-enhanced T1-weighted imaging. Initial dynamic contrast-enhanced T1-weighted images are obtained using ultrafast imaging with various reconstruction methods, followed by conventional contrast-enhanced sequences obtained at two and four minutes after contrast injection. For FP-MRI, various protocols commonly used for cancer diagnosis can be employed, with the procedure taking approximately 15&#8211;30 minutes, depending on the preexisting protocol of each institution. The details of the AB-MRI and FP-MRI protocols are presented in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Detailed abbreviated and full-protocol magnetic resonance imaging protocols of each institution</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jbc-28-427-i001.jpg"/><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><col width="1.69%" span="1"/><col width="1.69%" span="1"/><col width="16.44%" span="1"/><col width="17.82%" span="1"/><col width="17.82%" span="1"/><col width="9.52%" span="1"/><col width="11.67%" span="1"/><col width="11.67%" span="1"/><col width="11.67%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Hospital</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Samsung Medical Center</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Inje University Paik Hospital</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Soonchunhyang University Seoul Hospital</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1" valign="top">Protocol</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">AB-MRI</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">FP-MRI</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">AB-MRI</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">FP-MRI</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">AB-MRI</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">FP-MRI</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Equipment</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Vendor</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Ingenia CX, MR 7700 (Philips)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Ingenia CX, MR 7700 (Philips)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">VIDA (Siemens)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">VIDA (Siemens)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">VIDA (Siemens)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">VIDA (Siemens)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Field strength</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">3.0T</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">3.0T</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">3.0T</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">3.0T</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">3.0T</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">3.0T</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Type of coil</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">8 channels</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">8 channels</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">8 channels</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">8 channels</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">8 channels</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">8 channels</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Acquisition time (min)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">10</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">30</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">10</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">20</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">10</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1" valign="top">Acquisition parameter</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Orientation</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Axial</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Axial</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Axial</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Axial</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Axial</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">Axial</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">In-plane resolution (mm<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&#8804; 1 &#215; 1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&#8804; 1 &#215; 1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&#8804; 1 &#215; 1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">&#8804; 1 &#215; 1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">0.51 &#215; 0.51</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1.02 &#215; 1.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" valign="top">Slice thickness (mm)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" valign="top">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Imaging sequences</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Pre-T1-WI (non-fat-suppressed)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Pre-T1-WI (fat-suppressed)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">DCE-MRI, 1st phase</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">DCE-MRI, 2nd phase</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">DCE-MRI, 3rd phase</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">DCE-MRI, 4th phase</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">DCE-MRI, 5th phase</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Temporal resolution for DCE (min)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">1.35</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">1.35</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">1.32</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">1.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">T2-WI (fat-suppressed)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">T2-WI (non-fat-suppressed)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">DWI</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Ultrafast imaging</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Method</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Key-hole</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Key-hole</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Compressed sensing</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Compressed sensing</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Compressed sensing</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">Temporal resolution (sec)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">3.4</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">3.4</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">7.6</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">4.9</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">4.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">No. of phase</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">18</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">18</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">14</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">18</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1" style="background-color:rgb(229,226,240)" valign="top">17</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><p>AB-MRI = abbreviated magnetic resonance imaging; FP-MRI = full-protocol magnetic resonance imaging; WI = weighted imaging; DCE = dynamic contrast-enhanced; MRI = magnetic resonance imaging; DWI = diffusion-weighted imaging.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Image interpretation</title><p>Breast radiologists at each site, blinded to the results of other studies, independently will interpret the mammograms, ultrasonograms, and MRI scans. Mammographic breast density and background echotexture for mammography and ultrasonography, as well as background parenchymal enhancement and fibroglandular tissue for MRI, will be evaluated based on the BI-RADS classification. Additionally, for receiver operating characteristic curve analysis, the probability of malignancy will be assessed on a scale of 0% to 100%. Details of image interpretation and lesion management are presented in <xref rid="S2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Data 2</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Development and application of PRO measurement</title><p>PRO measurements have been developed to evaluate patients&#8217; experiences and preferences regarding MRI [<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. In this study, we aim to survey participants regarding their willingness to undergo repeat examinations using AB-MRI and FP-MRI and to assess their preferences as well as levels of discomfort, anxiety, and pain associated with MRI. After each imaging session, participants will respond through individual links to the PRO assessment to ensure the confidentiality of their personal information and eliminate any potential researcher interference. Details of the PRO are presented in <xref rid="S3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Data 3</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Main outcomes and measures</title><p>The primary outcomes are cancer detection rates (CDRs) on ultrasonography, AB-MRI, and FP-MRI. Secondary outcomes include the invasive CDR, abnormal interpretation rate, sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value, negative predictive value, and accuracy of each imaging modality, such as mammography, ultrasonography, AB-MRI, and FP-MRI. Interval cancer rates will be calculated. Detailed definitions of the outcome measures are presented in <xref rid="S2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Data 2</xref>. PROs are assessed in the study participants to assess whether they experienced MRI-related distress, the degree of distress if present, and their preferences for AB-MRI and FP-MRI. The PRO also asks participants which breast examination they prefer: mammography, ultrasonography, or MRI.</p></sec><sec><title>Sample size/power calculation</title><p>The primary objectives are to compare the CDR between ultrasonography and AB-MRI and between ultrasonography and FP-MRI. The sample size of the study was chosen to detect a significant difference in the CDR between ultrasonography and at least one of the two MRI protocols using a two-sided McNemar&#8217;s test with 80% power and an overall type I error rate of 0.05. Multiplicity due to the dual primary objectives was adjusted using Bonferroni&#8217;s correction method, which set the type I error rate for each comparison at 0.025. The CDRs of both AB-MRI and FP-MRI were assumed to be 11.7/1,000, whereas the CDR of ultrasonography was assumed to be 4.3/1,000, based on data reported by Baek et al. [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The discordant pair rate between ultrasonography and AB-MRI (or FP-MRI) was assumed to be 8/1,000. Based on these assumptions, 1,317 participants are required, and a total of 1,756 participants will be enrolled, accounting for a 25% dropout rate.</p></sec><sec><title>Screening failure and dropout criteria</title><p>Participants who withdrew their informed consent prior to the first round of examinations will be regarded as screening failure. Patients who do not undergo the next examinations within one month before or after the appropriate interval from the previous examination will be disqualified and classified as dropouts. Participants diagnosed with malignancy in any screening round will not continue to undergo subsequent assessments and will be classified as dropouts, as per the protocol.</p></sec><sec><title>Data collection</title><p>Data will be collected using the eCRF (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://postopdensemri.crf.kr" ext-link-type="uri">https://postopdensemri.crf.kr</ext-link>). Investigators or designated qualified staff at each institution will enter the participant data obtained from mammography, ultrasonography, AB-MRI, and FP-MRI into the eCRF during surveillance. Access to the eCRF system requires a valid username and password to ensure the security of participant data. Access to de-identified data will be restricted to investigators and authorized study personnel at each center.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical methods</title><p>Continuous variables will be summarized using standard descriptive statistics, including the mean, standard deviation, median, and interquartile range, and will be compared between the two groups (AB-MRI/FP-MRI and FP-MRI/AB-MRI) using either the independent <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test or the Mann&#8211;Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic> test, as appropriate. Categorical variables will be presented as counts and proportions and will be compared using the &#967;<sup>2</sup> test or Fisher&#8217;s exact test, as appropriate.</p><p>Pairwise comparisons across imaging modalities in a within-participant design will be performed using a two-sided McNemar&#8217;s test for CDR, sensitivity, and specificity and binary logistic regression analysis with generalized estimating equations (GEEs) for positive predictive value and negative predictive value. The area under the receiver operating characteristic curve will be estimated for each imaging modality and compared using a method that accounted for the correlation between paired observations [<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Additionally, a non-inferiority test for the CDR between AB-MRI and FP-MRI will be conducted using the methods described by Liu et al. [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Subgroup analyses according to age (&lt; 50 vs. &#8805; 50 years), menopausal status (premenopausal vs. postmenopausal), mammographic breast density (dense vs. non-dense), and molecular subtype will also be performed using the same statistical methods described previously, including McNemar&#8217;s test and logistic regression analysis with GEE. PROs related to participants&#8217; experiences and preferences will be compared between ultrasonography and MRI, as well as between AB-MRI and FP-MRI, using regression analysis with GEE. In addition, subgroup analyses by institutions will be conducted for PRO comparisons.</p><p>All reported <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values will be two-sided. Statistical significance will be defined as a <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05. To control for the inflation of family-wise type I error rate due to multiple comparisons, Bonferroni&#8217;s correction will be applied. No imputation of missing data or interim analyses will be performed. All statistical analyses will be performed using SAS version 9.4 (SAS Institute, Cary, USA).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Here, we present the design and protocol of a prospective, multicenter study comparing ultrasonography and MRI for SBC surveillance in patients with dense breasts and PHBC. AB-MRI has a diagnostic performance comparable to that of FP-MRI [<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref><xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Kim et al. [<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] recently compared the results of AB-MRI and FP-MRI in 726 propensity score-matched patients with PHBC, all of whom were examined under similar conditions. The sensitivity outcomes were comparable, whereas AB-MRI demonstrated significantly higher specificity. There were no significant differences in interval cancer rates and BI-RADS category 3 rates between the two groups. However, the published studies were retrospective, and no prospective data were available. Additionally, because the reported performances of AB-MRI and FP-MRI are comparable, conducting a non-inferiority test for diagnostic performance requires a sample size exceeding 18,000, which makes validation particularly challenging. Furthermore, despite retrospective evidence supporting the usefulness of AB-MRI, prospective studies directly comparing AB-MRI with ultrasonography and mammography for SBC surveillance in women with PHBC and dense breasts are still lacking.</p><p>In this trial, participants will undergo two sets of mammography, ultrasonography, and MRI&#8212;either AB-MRI or FP-MRI&#8212;over a 1-year interval for two years. Whether AB-MRI or FP-MRI should be performed is determined according to a predetermined randomization schedule. Breast radiologists will perform all imaging interpretations, and the diagnostic accuracy will be compared between ultrasonography and AB-MRI, as well as between ultrasonography and FP-MRI. Furthermore, CDRs will be compared between ultrasonography and AB-MRI, as well as between ultrasonography and FP-MRI. The PRO results for AB-MRI and FP-MRI will be compared. We expect that if MRI demonstrates superior diagnostic performance compared with ultrasonography, the diagnostic performances of AB-MRI and FP-MRI are comparable, and the PRO results of AB-MRI are also comparable with or better than those of FP-MRI, it will be reasonable to consider shifting the protocol from FP-MRI to AB-MRI [<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Furthermore, our results will provide evidence supporting the clinical implementation of AB-MRI. The study findings will be disseminated through peer-reviewed journals and conference presentations. Currently, no plans for the release of public data are available.</p><p>Two points warrant explicit clarification. First, the scope of blinded imaging interpretation: in line with prior prospective comparative studies [<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref><xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], each modality will be interpreted independently at each visit, with readers blinded to the other modality&#8217;s same-visit results; prior imaging and relevant histopathology will remain available to reflect routine surveillance and ensure patient safety, and all interpretations will follow prespecified, modality-specific protocols. Second, between-site differences in FP-MRI acquisition time: because each institution will use its routine protocol, FP-MRI scan times will vary modestly across sites; we retained local protocols to preserve external validity, and comparative analyses will account for site with prespecified subgroup/sensitivity analyses by site and by scan-time category.</p><p>In summary, this clinical trial is a prospective, multicenter cohort study designed to compare the diagnostic performance of ultrasonography and AB-MRI, as well as ultrasonography and FP-MRI, for SBC detection in women with dense breasts and PHBC. Patient enrollment is currently ongoing.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This study was funded by the Korean Society of Breast Imaging and Korean Society for Breast Screening (KSBI &amp; KSFBS-2023-01), the Korean Breast Cancer Study Group (KBCSG-27). This study was supported by an investigator-initiated research fund from Bayer Korea.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Conflicts of Interest:</bold> The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Data Availability:</bold> In accordance with the ICMJE data sharing policy, the authors have agreed to make the data available upon request.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><bold>Author Contributions:</bold>
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold>Kim K, Ko ES.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Funding acquisition:</bold>Ko ES.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Investigation:</bold>Chang YW, Park YM, Kim MK.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Methodology:</bold>Kim K, Kim MJ.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Project administration:</bold>Park YM.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supervision:</bold>Kim K, Yu J, Ko ES.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Validation:</bold>Kim K, Yu J, Ko ES.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Writing - original draft:</bold>Chang YW, Ko ES.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Writing - review &amp; editing:</bold>Yu J, Ko ES.</p></list-item></list>
</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wapnir</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dignam</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mamounas</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prognosis after ipsilateral breast tumor recurrence and locoregional recurrences in patients treated by breast-conserving therapy in five National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project protocols of node-negative breast cancer</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2009</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>2466</fpage><lpage>2473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19349544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1200/JCO.2008.19.8424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2684852</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Komoike</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iino</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akashi-Tanaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohsumi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ipsilateral breast tumor recurrence (IBTR) after breast-conserving treatment for early breast cancer: risk factors and impact on distant metastases</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>2006</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16333848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cncr.21551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Houssami</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciatto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonardi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early detection of second breast cancers improves prognosis in breast cancer survivors</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source><year>2009</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1505</fpage><lpage>1510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19297316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/annonc/mdp037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Post</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonnema</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van de Velde</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Bock</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact on survival of early detection of isolated breast recurrences after the primary treatment for breast cancer: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source><year>2009</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18421576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10549-008-0023-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khatcheressian</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hurley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bantug</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esserman</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grunfeld</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halberg</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Breast cancer follow-up and management after primary treatment: American Society of Clinical Oncology clinical practice guideline update</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2013</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>961</fpage><lpage>965</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23129741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1200/JCO.2012.45.9859</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuriyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Age-specific interval breast cancers in Japan: estimation of the proper sensitivity of screening using a population-based cancer registry</article-title><source>Cancer Sci</source><year>2008</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>2264</fpage><lpage>2267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18795941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1349-7006.2008.00926.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11159881</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tyne</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bougatsos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Screening for breast cancer: an update for the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>727</fpage><lpage>737</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19920273</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1059/0003-4819-151-10-200911170-00009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2972726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of dense breasts using screening mammography in Korean women: a retrospective observational study</article-title><source>Epidemiol Health</source><year>2014</year><volume>36</volume><elocation-id>e2014027</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25381996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4178/epih/e2014027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4258717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buist</surname><given-names>DSM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerlikowske</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miglioretti</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cumulative risk distribution for interval invasive second breast cancers after negative surveillance mammography</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2018</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>2070</fpage><lpage>2077</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29718790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1200/JCO.2017.76.8267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6036621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lehrer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jong</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pisano</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Detection of breast cancer with addition of annual screening ultrasound or a single screening MRI to mammography in women with elevated breast cancer risk</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2012</year><volume>307</volume><fpage>1394</fpage><lpage>1404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22474203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2012.388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3891886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohuchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sobue</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sensitivity and specificity of mammography and adjunctive ultrasonography to screen for breast cancer in the Japan Strategic Anti-cancer Randomized Trial (J-START): a randomised controlled trial</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2016</year><volume>387</volume><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26547101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(15)00774-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hooley</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stackhouse</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geisel</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Philpotts</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening US in patients with mammographically dense breasts: initial experience with Connecticut Public Act 09-41</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2012</year><volume>265</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22723501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1148/radiol.12120621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Melnikow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fenton</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitlock</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miglioretti</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weyrich</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Supplemental screening for breast cancer in women with dense breasts: a systematic review for the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26757021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7326/M15-1789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5100826</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rebolj</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Assi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brentnall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parmar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Addition of ultrasound to mammography in the case of dense breast tissue: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>2018</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>1559</fpage><lpage>1570</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29736009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41416-018-0080-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6008336</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sprague</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stout</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schechter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Ravesteyn</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cevik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alagoz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Benefits, harms, and cost-effectiveness of supplemental ultrasonography screening for women with dense breasts</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25486550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7326/M14-0692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4314343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plewes</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Causer</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zubovits</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jong</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Surveillance of <italic toggle="yes">BRCA1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">BRCA2</italic> mutation carriers with magnetic resonance imaging, ultrasound, mammography, and clinical breast examination</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2004</year><volume>292</volume><fpage>1317</fpage><lpage>1325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15367553</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.292.11.1317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhl</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schrading</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leutner</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morakkabati-Spitz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wardelmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fimmers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mammography, breast ultrasound, and magnetic resonance imaging for surveillance of women at high familial risk for breast cancer</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2005</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>8469</fpage><lpage>8476</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16293877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1200/JCO.2004.00.4960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monticciolo</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Newell</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monsees</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sickles</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breast cancer screening in women at higher-than-average risk: recommendations from the ACR</article-title><source>J Am Coll Radiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>408</fpage><lpage>414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29371086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jacr.2017.11.034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identifying effective supplemental screening strategies for women with a personal history of breast cancer</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2020</year><volume>295</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32101092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1148/radiol.2020200015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7104698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhl</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schrading</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strobel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schild</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilgers</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bieling</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abbreviated breast magnetic resonance imaging (MRI): first postcontrast subtracted images and maximum-intensity projection-a novel approach to breast cancer screening with MRI</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2014</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>2304</fpage><lpage>2310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24958821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1200/JCO.2013.52.5386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baek</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of abbreviated MRI with mammography and ultrasound in women with a personal history of breast cancer</article-title><source>Acad Radiol</source><year>2022</year><volume>29</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><fpage>S19</fpage><lpage>S25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34175207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.acra.2021.05.022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Panigrahi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Falomo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panigrahi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An abbreviated protocol for high-risk screening breast magnetic resonance imaging: impact on performance metrics and BI-RADS assessment</article-title><source>Acad Radiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1132</fpage><lpage>1138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28506511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.acra.2017.03.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Usefulness of abbreviated breast MRI screening for women with a history of breast cancer surgery</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source><year>2018</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29030785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10549-017-4530-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the diagnostic performance of abbreviated MRI and full diagnostic MRI using a computer-aided diagnosis (CAD) system in patients with a personal history of breast cancer: the effect of CAD-generated kinetic features on reader performance</article-title><source>Clin Radiol</source><year>2019</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>817.e15</fpage><lpage>817.e21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.crad.2019.06.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31362885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#8217;Orsi</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sickles</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mendelson</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><source>ACR-BI-RADS<sup>&#9415;</sup> Atlas, Breast Imaging Reporting and Data System</source><publisher-loc>Reston</publisher-loc><publisher-name>American College of Radiology</publisher-name><year>2013</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Measuring patient-reported distress from breast magnetic resonance imaging: development and validation of the MRI-related distress scale (MRI-DS)</article-title><source>Cancer Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>e70089</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39126264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cam4.70089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11316135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeLong</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeLong</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke-Pearson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparing the areas under two or more correlated receiver operating characteristic curves: a nonparametric approach</article-title><source>Biometrics</source><year>1988</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>837</fpage><lpage>845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3203132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsueh</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tests for equivalence or non-inferiority for paired binary data</article-title><source>Stat Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11782062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/sim.1012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Abbreviated screening MRI for women with a history of breast cancer: comparison with full-protocol breast MRI</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2022</year><volume>305</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35699580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1148/radiol.213310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herschorn</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sprague</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buist</surname><given-names>DSM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Newell</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Imaging surveillance options for individuals with a personal history of breast cancer: <italic toggle="yes">AJR</italic> expert panel narrative review</article-title><source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source><year>2022</year><volume>219</volume><fpage>854</fpage><lpage>868</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35544374</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2214/AJR.22.27635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9691521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>VY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diffusion-weighted magnetic resonance imaging for breast cancer screening in high-risk women: design and imaging protocol of a prospective multicenter study in Korea</article-title><source>J Breast Cancer</source><year>2021</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33913277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4048/jbc.2021.24.e19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8090809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Breast cancer screening with mammography plus ultrasonography or magnetic resonance imaging in women 50 years or younger at diagnosis and treated with breast conservation therapy</article-title><source>JAMA Oncol</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1495</fpage><lpage>1502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28655029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamaoncol.2017.1256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5710190</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS</title><supplementary-material id="S1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Data 1</title><p>Case report forms for study</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jbc-28-427-s001.doc" id="d67e2014" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="S2" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Data 2</title><p>Supplementary methods</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jbc-28-427-s002.doc" id="d67e2019" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="S3" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Data 3</title><p>Patient-reported outcome measurement for the study</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jbc-28-427-s003.doc" id="d67e2024" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></back></article></pmc-articleset>